{"text": "Chapter 1 After a year of slavery in the Salt Mines of Endovier, Celaena Sardothien was accustomed to being escorted everywhere in shackles and at sword-point. Most of the thousands of slaves in Endovier received similar treatment—though an extra half-dozen guards always walked Celaena to and from the mines. That was expected by Adarlan's most notorious assassin. What she did not usually expect, however, was a hooded man in black at her side—as there was now. He gripped her arm as he led her through the shining building in which most of Endovier's officials and overseers were housed. They strode down corridors, up flights of stairs, and around and around until she hadn't the slightest chance of finding her way out again. At least, that was her escort's intention, because she hadn't failed to notice when they went up and down the same staircase within a matter of minutes. Nor had she missed when they zigzagged between levels, even though the building was a standard grid of hallways and stairwells. As if she'd lose her bearings that easily. She might have been insulted if he wasn't trying so hard. They entered a particularly long hallway, silent save for their footsteps. Though the man grasping her arm was tall and fit, she could see nothing of the features concealed beneath his hood. Another tactic meant to confuse and intimidate her. The black clothes were probably a part of it, too. His head shifted in her direction, and Celaena flashed him a grin. He looked forward again, his iron grip tightening.", "entities": [{"start": 55, "end": 63, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 65, "end": 83, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena Sardothien"}, {"start": 65, "end": 72, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 195, "end": 203, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 279, "end": 286, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 331, "end": 338, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 543, "end": 551, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 1446, "end": 1453, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C01.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "It was flattering, she supposed, even if she didn't know what was happening, or why he'd been waiting for her outside the mine shaft. After a day of cleaving rock salt from the innards of the mountain, finding him standing there with six guards hadn't improved her mood. But her ears had pricked when he'd introduced himself to her overseer as Chaol Westfall, Captain of the Royal Guard, and suddenly, the sky loomed, the mountains pushed from behind, and even the earth swelled toward her knees. She hadn't tasted fear in a while—hadn't let herself taste fear. When she awoke every morning, she repeated the same words: Iwill not be afraid . For a year, those words had meant the difference between breaking and bending; they had kept her from shattering in the darkness of the mines. Not that she'd let the captain know any of that. Celaena examined the gloved hand holding her arm. The dark leather almost matched the dirt on her skin. She adjusted her torn and filthy tunic with her free hand and held in her sigh. Entering the mines before sunrise and departing after dusk, she rarely glimpsed the sun. She was frightfully pale beneath the dirt. It was true that she had been attractive once, beautiful even, but— well, it didn't matter now, did it? They turned down another hallway, and she studied the stranger's finely crafted sword. Its shimmering pommel was shaped like an eagle midflight. Noticing her stare, his gloved hand descended to rest upon its golden head. Another smile tugged at the corners of her lips. “You're a long way from Rifthold, Captain,” she said, clearing her throat.", "entities": [{"start": 344, "end": 358, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol Westfall"}, {"start": 344, "end": 349, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 835, "end": 842, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1549, "end": 1557, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Rifthold"}], "chapter_id": "C01.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“Did you come with the army Iheard thumping around earlier?” She peered into the darkness beneath his hood but saw nothing. Still, she felt his eyes upon her face, judging, weighing, testing. She stared right back. The Captain of the Royal Guard would be an interesting opponent. Maybe even worthy of some effort on her part. Finally, the man raised his sword hand, and the folds of his cloak fell to conceal the blade. As his cloak shifted, she spied the gold wyvern embroidered on his tunic. The royal seal. “What do you care for the armies of Adarlan?” he replied. How lovely it was to hear a voice like her own—cool and articulate—even if he was a nasty brute! “Nothing,” she said, shrugging. He let out a low growl of annoyance. Oh, it'd be nice to see his blood spill across the marble. She'd lost her temper once before—once, when her first overseer chose the wrong day to push her too hard. She still remembered the feeling of embedding the pickax into his gut, and the stickiness of his blood on her hands and face. She could disarm two of these guards in a heartbeat. Would the captain fare better than her late overseer? Contemplating the potential outcomes, she grinned at him again. “Don't you look at me like that,” he warned, and his hand drifted back toward his sword. Celaena hid her smirk this time. They passed a series of wooden doors that she'd seen a few minutes ago. If she wanted to escape, she simply had to turn left at the next hallway and take the stairs down three flights.", "entities": [{"start": 234, "end": 245, "label": "ORG", "text": "Royal Guard"}, {"start": 546, "end": 553, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 1285, "end": 1292, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C01.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Chapter 2 “Your Highness,” said the Captain of the Guard. He straightened from a low bow and removed his hood, revealing close-cropped chestnut hair. The hood had definitely been meant to intimidate her into submission during their walk. As if that sort of trick could work on her . Despite her irritation, she blinked at the sight of his face. He was so young! Captain Westfall was not excessively handsome, but she couldn't help finding the ruggedness of his face and the clarity of his golden-brown eyes rather appealing. She cocked her head, now keenly aware of her wretched dirtiness. “This is she?” the Crown Prince of Adarlan asked, and Celaena's head whipped around as the captain nodded. Both of them stared at her, waiting for her to bow. When she remained upright, Chaol shifted on his feet, and the prince glanced at his captain before lifting his chin a bit higher. Bow to him indeed! If she were bound for the gallows, she would most certainly not spend the last moments of her life in groveling submission. Thundering steps issued from behind her, and someone grabbed her by the neck. Celaena only glimpsed crimson cheeks and a sandy mustache before being thrown to the icy marble floor. Pain slammed through her face, light splintering her vision. Her arms ached as her bound hands kept her joints from properly aligning. Though she tried to stop them, tears of pain welled. “ That is the proper way to greet your future king,” a red-faced man snapped at Celaena. The assassin hissed, baring her teeth as she twisted her head to look at the kneeling bastard.", "entities": [{"start": 362, "end": 378, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Captain Westfall"}, {"start": 625, "end": 632, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 644, "end": 651, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 776, "end": 781, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 1100, "end": 1107, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1471, "end": 1478, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C02.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "He was almost as large as her overseer, clothed in reds and oranges that matched his thinning hair. His obsidian eyes glittered as his grip tightened on her neck. If she could move her right arm just a few inches, she could throw him off balance and grab his sword… The shackles dug into her stomach, and fizzing, boiling rage turned her face scarlet. After a too-long moment, the Crown Prince spoke. “Idon't quite comprehend why you'd force someone to bow when the purpose of the gesture is to display allegiance and respect.” His words were coated with glorious boredom. Celaena tried to pivot a free eye to the prince, but could only see a pair of black leather boots against the white floor. “It's clear that you respect me, Duke Perrington, but it's a bit unnecessary to put such effort into forcing Celaena Sardothien to have the same opinion. You and Iknow very well she has no love for my family. So perhaps your intent is to humiliate her.” He paused, and she could have sworn his eyes fell on her face. “But Ithink she's had enough of that.” He stopped for another moment, then asked: “Don't you have a meeting with Endovier's treasurer? Iwouldn't want you to be late, especially when you came all this way to meet with him.” Understanding the dismissal, her tormentor grunted and released her. Celaena peeled her cheek from the marble but lay on the floor until he stood and left. If she managed to escape, perhaps she'd hunt down this Duke Perrington fellow and return the warmth of his greeting.", "entities": [{"start": 573, "end": 580, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 729, "end": 744, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Duke Perrington"}, {"start": 805, "end": 812, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 805, "end": 823, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena Sardothien"}, {"start": 1126, "end": 1134, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 1305, "end": 1312, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1447, "end": 1462, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Duke Perrington"}], "chapter_id": "C02.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "As she rose, she frowned at the imprint of grit she left behind on the otherwise spotless floor, and at the clank of her shackles echoing through the silent room. But she'd been trained to be an assassin since the age of eight, since the day the King of the Assassins found her half-dead on the banks of a frozen river and brought her to his keep. She wouldn't be humiliated by anything, least of all being dirty. Gathering her pride, she tossed her long braid behind a shoulder and lifted her head. Her eyes met those of the prince. Dorian Havilliard smiled at her. It was a polished smile, and reeked of court-trained charm. Sprawled across the throne, he had his chin propped by a hand, his golden crown glinting in the soft light. On his black doublet, an emblazoned gold rendering of the royal wyvern occupied the entirety of the chest. His red cloak fell gracefully around him and his throne. Yet there was something in his eyes, strikingly blue—the color of the waters of the southern countries—and the way they contrasted with his raven-black hair that made her pause. He was achingly handsome, and couldn't have been older than twenty. Princes are not supposed to be handsome ! They're sniveling, stupid, repulsive creatures ! This one… this… How unfair of him to be royal and beautiful . She shifted on her feet as he frowned, surveying her in turn. “Ithought Iasked you to clean her,” he said to Captain Westfall, who stepped forward. She'd forgotten there was anyone else in the room. She looked at her rags and stained skin, and she couldn't suppress the twinge of shame.", "entities": [{"start": 246, "end": 267, "label": "PERSON", "text": "King of the Assassins"}, {"start": 534, "end": 551, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian Havilliard"}, {"start": 534, "end": 540, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 1407, "end": 1423, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Captain Westfall"}], "chapter_id": "C02.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Chapter 3 The prince's eyes shone with amusement at her brashness but lingered a bit too long on her body. Celaena could have raked her nails down his face for staring at her like that, yet the fact that he'd even bother to look when she was in such a filthy state… Aslow smile spread across her face. The prince crossed his long legs. “Leave us,” he ordered the guards. “Chaol, stay where you are.” Celaena stepped closer as the guards shuffled out, shutting the door. Foolish, foolish move. But Chaol's face remained unreadable. He couldn't honestly believe he'd contain her if she tried to escape! She straightened her spine. What were they planning that would make them so irresponsible? The prince chuckled. “Don't you think it's risky to be so bold with me when your freedom is on the line?” Of all the things he could have said, that was what she had least expected. “My freedom?” At the sound of the word, she saw a land of pine and snow, of sun-bleached cliffs and white-capped seas, a land where light was swallowed in the velvety green of bumps and hollows—a land that she had forgotten. “Yes, your freedom. So, Ihighly suggest, Miss Sardothien, that you get your arrogance in check before you end up back in the mines.” The prince uncrossed his legs. “Though perhaps your attitude will be useful. I'm not going to pretend that my father's empire was built on trust and understanding. But you already know that.” Her fingers curled as she waited for him to continue. His eyes met hers, probing, intent.", "entities": [{"start": 107, "end": 114, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 372, "end": 377, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 400, "end": 407, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 497, "end": 502, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}], "chapter_id": "C03.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“My father has gotten it into his head that he needs a Champion.” It took a delicious moment for her to understand. Celaena tipped back her head and laughed. “Your father wants me to be his Champion? What—don't tell me that he's managed to eliminate every noble soul out there! Surely there's one chivalrous knight, one lord of steadfast heart and courage.” “Mind your mouth,” Chaol warned from beside her. “What about you, hmm?” she said, raising her brows at the captain. Oh, it was too funny! Her —the King's Champion! “Our beloved king finds you lacking?” The captain put a hand on his sword. “If you'd be quiet, you'd hear the rest of what His Highness has to tell you.” She faced the prince. “Well?” Dorian leaned back in his throne. “My father needs someone to aid the empire —someone to help him maneuver around difficult people.” “You mean he needs a lackey for his dirty work.” “If you want to put it that bluntly, then, yes,” the prince said. “His Champion would keep his opponents quiet.” “As quiet as the grave,” she said sweetly. Asmile tugged on Dorian's lips, but he kept his face straight. “Yes.” To work for the King of Adarlan as his loyal servant. She raised her chin. To kill for him—to be a fang in the mouth of the beast that had already consumed half of Erilea… “And if Iaccept?” “Then, after six years, he'll grant you your freedom.” “Six years!” But the word “freedom” echoed through her once more. “If you decline,” Dorian said, anticipating her next question, “you'll remain in Endovier.” His sapphire eyes became hard, and she swallowed.", "entities": [{"start": 116, "end": 123, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 377, "end": 382, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 706, "end": 712, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 1061, "end": 1067, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 1130, "end": 1145, "label": "PERSON", "text": "King of Adarlan"}, {"start": 1138, "end": 1145, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 1278, "end": 1284, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Erilea"}, {"start": 1443, "end": 1449, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 1506, "end": 1514, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}], "chapter_id": "C03.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "And die here was what he didn't need to add. Six years as the king's crooked dagger… or a lifetime in Endovier. “However,” the prince said, “there's a catch.” She kept her face neutral as he toyed with a ring on his finger. “The position isn't being offered to you. Yet. My father thought to have a bit of fun. He's hosting a competition. He invited twenty-three members of his council to each sponsor a would-be Champion to train in the glass castle and ultimately compete in a duel. Were you to win,” he said with a half smile, “you'd officially be Adarlan's Assassin.” She didn't return his smile. “Who, exactly, are my competitors?” Seeing her expression, the prince's grin faded. “Thieves and assassins and warriors from across Erilea.” She opened her mouth, but he cut her off. “If you win, and prove yourself both skilled and trustworthy, my father has sworn to grant you your freedom. And , while you're his Champion, you'll receive a considerable salary.” She barely heard his last few words. Acompetition! Against some nobody men from the-gods-knew-where! And assassins! “What other assassins?” she demanded. “None that I've heard of. None as famous as you . And that reminds me —you won't be competing as Celaena Sardothien.” “What?” “You'll compete under an alias. Idon't suppose you heard about what happened after your trial.” “News is rather hard to come by when you're slaving in a mine.” Dorian chuckled, shaking his head. “No one knows that Celaena Sardothien is just a young woman —they all thought you were far older.” “What?” she asked again, her face flushing.", "entities": [{"start": 102, "end": 110, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 733, "end": 739, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Erilea"}, {"start": 1216, "end": 1223, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1216, "end": 1234, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena Sardothien"}, {"start": 1405, "end": 1411, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 1459, "end": 1466, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1459, "end": 1477, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena Sardothien"}], "chapter_id": "C03.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Chapter 4 When Celaena finally collapsed onto a bed after her meeting in the throne room, she couldn't fall asleep, despite the exhaustion in every inch of her body. After being roughly bathed by brutish servants, the wounds on her back throbbed and her face felt like it had been scrubbed to the bone. Shifting to lie on her side to ease the pain in her dressed and bound back, she ran her hand down the mattress, and blinked at the freeness of movement. Before she'd gotten into the bath, Chaol had removed her shackles. She'd felt everything —the reverberations of the key turning in the lock of her irons, then again as they loosened and fell to the floor. She could still feel the ghost chains hovering just above her skin. Looking up at the ceiling, she rotated her raw, burning joints and gave a sigh of contentment. But it was too strange to lie on a mattress, to have silk caress her skin and a pillow cradle her cheek. She had forgotten what food other than soggy oats and hard bread tasted like, what a clean body and clothes could do to a person. Now it was utterly foreign. Though her dinner hadn't been that wonderful. Not only was the roast chicken unimpressive, but after a few forkfuls, she'd dashed into the bathroom to deposit the contents of her stomach. She wanted to eat , to put a hand to a swollen belly, to wish that she'd never eaten a morsel and swear that she'd never eat again. She'd eat well in Rifthold, wouldn't she? And, more importantly, her stomach would adjust. She'd wasted away to nothing.", "entities": [{"start": 15, "end": 22, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 491, "end": 496, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 1425, "end": 1433, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Rifthold"}], "chapter_id": "C04.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Beneath her nightgown, her ribs reached out from inside of her, showing bones where flesh and meat should have been. And her breasts! Once well-formed, they were now no larger than they'd been in the midst of puberty. Alump clogged her throat, which she promptly swallowed down. The softness of the mattress smothered her, and she shifted again, lying on her back, despite the pain it gave her. Her face hadn't been much better when she glimpsed it in the washroom mirror. It was haggard: her cheekbones were sharp, her jaw pronounced, and her eyes slightly, but ever so disturbingly, sunken in. She took steadying breaths, savoring the hope. She'd eat. Alot. And exercise. She could be healthy again. Imagining outrageous feasts and regaining her former glory, she finally fell asleep. When Chaol came to fetch her the next morning, he found her sleeping on the floor, wrapped in a blanket. “Sardothien,” he said. She made a mumbling noise, burying her face farther into the pillow. “Why are you sleeping on the ground?” She opened an eye. Of course, he didn't mention how different she looked now that she was clean . She didn't bother concealing herself with the blanket as she stood. The yards of fabric they called a nightgown covered her enough. “The bed was uncomfortable,” she said simply, but quickly forgot the captain as she beheld the sunlight. Pure, fresh, warm sunlight. Sunlight that she could bask in day after day if she got her freedom, sunlight to drown out the endless dark of the mines. It leaked in through the heavy drapes, smearing itself across the room in thick lines.", "entities": [{"start": 792, "end": 797, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}], "chapter_id": "C04.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Gingerly, Celaena stretched out a hand. Her hand was pale, almost skeletal, but there was something about it, something beyond the bruises and cuts and scars, that seemed beautiful and new in the morning light. She ran to the window and nearly ripped the curtains from their hangings as she opened them to the gray mountains and bleakness of Endovier. The guards positioned beneath the window didn't glance upward, and she gaped at the bluish-gray sky, at the clouds slipping on their shoes and shuffling toward the horizon. Iwill not be afraid . For the first time in a while, the words felt true. Her lips peeled into a smile. The captain raised an eyebrow, but said nothing. She was cheerful —jubilant, really— and her mood improved when the servants coiled her braided hair onto the back of her head and dressed her in a surprisingly fine riding habit that concealed her miserably thin form. She loved clothes—loved the feeling of silk, of velvet, of satin, of suede and chiffon—and was fascinated by the grace of seams, the intricate perfection of an embossed surface. And when she won this ridiculous competition, when she was free… she could buy all the clothes she wanted. She laughed when Chaol, irked at how Celaena stood in front of the mirror for five minutes, admiring herself, half-dragged her out of the room. The budding sky made her want to dance and skip down the halls before they entered the main yard.", "entities": [{"start": 10, "end": 17, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 342, "end": 350, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 1198, "end": 1203, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 1218, "end": 1225, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C04.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Chapter 5 Celaena brushed a stray wisp of hair from her face and allowed herself to be led into the clearing. If she wanted to break free, she'd have to go through Chaol first. Had they been alone, she might have attempted it, though the chains would make it difficult; but with an entourage of royal guards trained to kill without hesitation… Chaol remained close beside her while a fire was kindled and food prepared from the boxes and sacks of supplies. The soldiers rolled logs to make small circles, where they sat while their companions stirred and fried. The Crown Prince's dogs, who had dutifully trotted alongside their master, approached the assassin with wagging tails and lay at her feet. At least someone was glad for her company. Hungry by the time a plate was finally laid in her lap, Celaena became a bit more than irritated when the captain did not immediately remove her irons. After giving her a long warning look, he unlocked her chains and clamped them onto her ankles. She only rolled her eyes as she raised a small portion of meat to her lips. She chewed slowly. The last thing she needed was to be sick in front of them. While the soldiers talked amongst themselves, Celaena took in their surroundings. She and Chaol sat with five soldiers. The Crown Prince, of course, sat with Perrington on their own two logs, far from her. While Dorian had been all arrogance and amusement the previous night, his features were grave as he spoke to the duke. His entire body seemed tensed, and she didn't fail to notice the way he clenched his jaw when Perrington spoke.", "entities": [{"start": 10, "end": 17, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 164, "end": 169, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 344, "end": 349, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 566, "end": 578, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Crown Prince"}, {"start": 800, "end": 807, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1191, "end": 1198, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1235, "end": 1240, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 1269, "end": 1281, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Crown Prince"}, {"start": 1303, "end": 1313, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Perrington"}, {"start": 1357, "end": 1363, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 1564, "end": 1574, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Perrington"}], "chapter_id": "C05.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Whatever their relationship was, it wasn't cordial. Midbite, Celaena tore her focus from the prince to study the trees. The forest had gone silent. The ebony hounds' ears were erect, though they didn't seem to be bothered by the stillness. Even the soldiers quieted. Her heart skipped a beat. The forest was different here. The leaves dangled like jewels—tiny droplets of ruby, pearl, topaz, amethyst, emerald, and garnet; and a carpet of such riches coated the forest floor around them. Despite the ravages of conquest, this part of Oakwald Forest remained untouched. It still echoed with the remnants of the power that had once given these trees such unnatural beauty. She'd been only eight when Arobynn Hamel, her mentor and the King of the Assassins, found her half-submerged on the banks of a frozen river and brought her to his keep on the border between Adarlan and Terrasen. While training her to be his finest and most loyal assassin, Arobynn had never allowed her to return home to Terrasen. But she still remembered the beauty of the world before the King of Adarlan had ordered so much of it burned. Now there was nothing left for her there, nor would there ever be. Arobynn had never said it aloud, but if she'd refused his offer to train her, he would have handed her to those who would have killed her. Or worse. She'd been newly orphaned, and even at eight, she knew that a life with Arobynn, with a new name that no one would recognize but someday everyone would fear, was a chance to start over. To escape the fate that led her to leap into the icy river that night ten years ago.", "entities": [{"start": 61, "end": 68, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 534, "end": 548, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Oakwald Forest"}, {"start": 698, "end": 711, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Arobynn Hamel"}, {"start": 698, "end": 705, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Arobynn"}, {"start": 861, "end": 868, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 873, "end": 881, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Terrasen"}, {"start": 944, "end": 951, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Arobynn"}, {"start": 992, "end": 1000, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Terrasen"}, {"start": 1070, "end": 1077, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 1179, "end": 1186, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Arobynn"}, {"start": 1400, "end": 1407, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Arobynn"}], "chapter_id": "C05.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“Damned forest,” said an olive-skinned soldier in their circle. Asoldier beside him chuckled. “The sooner it's burned, the better, Isay.” The other soldiers nodded, and Celaena stiffened. “It's full of hate,” said another. “Did you expect anything else?” she interrupted. Chaol's hand darted to his sword as the soldiers turned to her, some of them sneering. “This isn't just any forest.” She beckoned with her fork to the woods. “It's Brannon's forest.” “My father used to tell me stories about it being full of faeries,” a soldier said. “They're all gone now.” One took a bite from an apple, and said: “Along with those damned wretched Fae.” Another said: “We got rid of them, didn't we?” “I'd watch your tongues,” Celaena snapped. “King Brannon was Fae, and Oakwald is still his. Iwouldn't be surprised if some of the trees remember him.” The soldiers laughed. “They'd have to be two thousand years old, them trees!” said one. “Fae are immortal,” she said. “Trees ain't.” Bristling, Celaena shook her head and took another small forkful of food. “What do you know about this forest?” Chaol quietly asked her. Was he mocking her? The soldiers sat forward, poised to laugh. But the captain's golden-brown eyes held mere curiosity. She swallowed her meat. “Before Adarlan began its conquest, this forest was cloaked in magic,” she said softly, but not meekly. He waited for her to continue, but she had said enough. “And?” he prodded. “And that's all Iknow,” she said, meeting his gaze. Disappointed at the lack of anything to mock, the soldiers returned to their meals.", "entities": [{"start": 169, "end": 176, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 272, "end": 277, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 638, "end": 641, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Fae"}, {"start": 717, "end": 724, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 735, "end": 747, "label": "PERSON", "text": "King Brannon"}, {"start": 752, "end": 755, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Fae"}, {"start": 931, "end": 934, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Fae"}, {"start": 986, "end": 993, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1087, "end": 1092, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 1264, "end": 1271, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}], "chapter_id": "C05.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Chapter 6 For the next two weeks, they traveled down through the continent, the nights becoming colder, the days shorter. Icy rain kept them company for four days, during which time Celaena was so miserably cold that she contemplated throwing herself into a ravine, hopefully dragging Chaol with her. Everything was wet and half-frozen, and while she could bear sodden hair, she couldn't withstand the agony of wet shoes. She had little sensation in her toes. Each night, she wrapped them in whatever spare, dry clothing she could find. She felt as though she were in a state of partial decay, and with each gust of frigid, stinging wind, she wondered when her skin would rip from her bones. But, as it was autumn weather, the rain suddenly disappeared, and cloudless, brilliant skies once more stretched over them. Celaena was half-asleep on her horse when the Crown Prince pulled out of line and came trotting toward them, his dark hair bouncing. His red cape rose and fell in a crimson wave. Above his unadorned white shirt was a fine cobalt-blue jerkin trimmed with gold. She would have snorted, but he did look rather good in his knee-high brown boots. And his leather belt did go nicely —even though the hunting knife seemed a bit too bejeweled. He pulled up alongside Chaol. “Come,” he said to the captain, and jerked his head at the steep, grassy hill that the company was starting to ascend. “Where?” the captain asked, jangling Celaena's chain for Dorian to notice. Wherever he went, she went. “Come see the view,” Dorian clarified. “Bring that one, Isuppose.” Celaena bristled. “That one”!", "entities": [{"start": 182, "end": 189, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 285, "end": 290, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 816, "end": 823, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1275, "end": 1280, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 1438, "end": 1445, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1458, "end": 1464, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 1525, "end": 1531, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 1571, "end": 1578, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C06.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "As if she were a piece of baggage! Chaol moved them out of line, giving her chain a fierce tug. She grasped the reins as they advanced into a gallop, the tangy smell of horsehair creeping into her nostrils. They rode quickly up the steep hill, the horse jerking and surging beneath her. Celaena tried not to wince as she slid backward in the saddle. If she fell, she'd die of humiliation. But the setting sun emerged from the trees behind them, and her breath caught in her throat as a spire, then three, then six more appeared, piercing the sky. Atop the hill, Celaena stared at the crowning achievement of Adarlan. The glass castle of Rifthold. It was gargantuan, a vertical city of shimmering, crystalline towers and bridges, chambers and turrets, domed ballrooms and long, endless hallways. It had been built above the original stone castle, and cost a kingdom's wealth to construct. She thought of the first time she'd seen it, eight years ago, cold and still, frozen like the earth beneath her fat pony. Even then, she found the castle tasteless, a waste of resources and talent, its towers reaching into the sky like clawed fingers. She remembered the powder-blue cloak that she kept touching, the weight of her fresh curls, the scratch of her stockings against the saddle, how she'd worried about the spot of mud on her red velvet shoes, and how she kept on thinking about that man—the man she'd killed three days earlier. “One more tower and the whole thing will collapse,” the Crown Prince said from his spot on the other side of Chaol. The sounds of their approaching party filled the air.", "entities": [{"start": 35, "end": 40, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 287, "end": 294, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 562, "end": 569, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 608, "end": 615, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 637, "end": 645, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Rifthold"}, {"start": 1540, "end": 1545, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}], "chapter_id": "C06.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“We've still got a few miles left, and I'd rather navigate these foothills in the daylight. We'll camp here tonight.” “Iwonder what your father will think of her,” Chaol said. “Oh, he'll be fine—until she opens her mouth. Then the bellowing and the blustering will begin, and I'll regret wasting the past two months tracking her down. But—well, Ithink my father has more important matters to worry over.” With that, the prince moved off. Celaena couldn't keep her eyes from the castle. She felt so small, even from far away. She'd forgotten how dwarfing the building was. The soldiers scurried about, lighting fires and raising tents. “You look as if you're facing the gallows, not your freedom,” the captain said beside her. She wound and unwound a strap of leather rein around a finger. “It's odd to see it.” “The city?” “The city, the castle, the slums, the river.” The shadow of the castle grew across the city like a hulking beast. “Istill don't entirely know how it happened.” “How you were captured?” She nodded. “Despite your visions of a perfect world under an empire, your rulers and politicians are quick to destroy each other. So are assassins, Isuppose.” “You believe one of your kind betrayed you?” “Everyone knew Ireceived the best hires and could demand any payment.” She scanned the twisting city streets and the winding glimmer of the river. “Were Igone, a vacancy would arise from which they could profit. It might have been one; it might have been many.” “You shouldn't expect to find honor amongst such company.” “Ididn't say that Idid.", "entities": [{"start": 164, "end": 169, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 438, "end": 445, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C06.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Chapter 7 Trumpeters signaled their arrival as they passed through the looming alabaster walls of Rifthold. Crimson flags depicting gold wyverns flapped in the wind above the capital city, the cobblestone streets were cleared of traffic, and Celaena, unchained, dressed, painted, and seated in front of Chaol, frowned as the odor of the city met her nose. Beneath the smell of spices and horses lay a foundation of filth, blood, and spoiled milk. The air held a hint of the salty waters of the Avery—different from the salt of Endovier. This brought with it warships from every ocean in Erilea, merchant vessels crammed with goods and slaves, and fishing boats with half-rotted, scale-covered flesh that people somehow managed to eat. From bearded peddlers to servant girls carrying armfuls of hatboxes, everyone paused as the flag bearers trotted proudly ahead, and Dorian Havilliard waved. They followed the Crown Prince, who, like Chaol, was swathed in a red cape, pinned over the left breast with a brooch fashioned after the royal seal. The prince wore a golden crown upon his neat hair, and she had to concede that he looked rather regal. Young women flocked to them, waving. Dorian winked and grinned. Celaena couldn't help but notice the sharp stares from the same women when they beheld her in the prince's retinue. She knew how she appeared, seated atop a horse like some prize lady being brought to the castle. So Celaena only smiled at them, tossed her hair, and batted her eyelashes at the prince's back. Her arm stung. “What?” she hissed at the Captain of the Guard as he pinched her.", "entities": [{"start": 98, "end": 106, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Rifthold"}, {"start": 242, "end": 249, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 303, "end": 308, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 494, "end": 499, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Avery"}, {"start": 587, "end": 593, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Erilea"}, {"start": 867, "end": 884, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian Havilliard"}, {"start": 867, "end": 873, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 934, "end": 939, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 1182, "end": 1188, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 1209, "end": 1216, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1425, "end": 1432, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C07.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“You look ridiculous,” he said through his teeth, smiling at the crowd. She mirrored his expression. “ They're ridiculous.” “Be quiet and act normally.” His breath was hot on her neck. “Ishould jump from the horse and run,” she said, waving at a young man, who gaped at what he thought was a court lady's attention. “I'd vanish in an instant.” “Yes,” he said, “you'd vanish with three arrows buried in your spine.” “Such pleasant talk.” They entered the shopping district, where the crowd swelled between the trees lining the broad avenues of white stone. The glass storefronts were nearly invisible beyond the crowd, but a ravenous sort of hunger arose in her as they passed shop after shop. Each window displayed dresses and tunics, which stood proudly behind lines of sparkling jewelry and broad-rimmed hats clumped together like bouquets of flowers. Above it all, the glass castle loomed, so high she had to tilt her head back to see the uppermost towers. Why had they chosen such a long and inconvenient route? Did they really wish to parade about? Celaena swallowed. There was a break in the buildings, and sails spread like moth's wings greeted them as they turned onto the avenue along the Avery. Ships sat docked along the pier, a mess of rope and netting with sailors calling to each other, too busy to notice the royal procession. At the sound of a whip, her head snapped to the side. Slaves staggered down the gangplank of a merchant ship. Amix of conquered nations bound together, each of them had the hollow, raging face she'd seen so many times before.", "entities": [{"start": 1054, "end": 1061, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1198, "end": 1203, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Avery"}], "chapter_id": "C07.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Most of the slaves were prisoners of war—rebels who survived the butchering blocks and endless lines of Adarlan's armies. Some were probably people who had been caught or accused of trying to practice magic. But others were just ordinary folk, in the wrong place at the wrong time. Now that she noticed, there were countless chained slaves working the docks, lifting and sweating, holding parasols and pouring water, eyes on the ground or the sky—never on what was before them. She wanted to leap from her horse and run to them, or to simply scream that she wasn't a part of this prince's court, that she had no hand in bringing them here, chained and starved and beaten, that she had worked and bled with them, with their families and friends—she was not like these monsters that destroyed everything. That she had done something, nearly two years ago, when she had freed almost two hundred slaves from the Pirate Lord. Even that, though, wasn't enough. The city was suddenly separate, ripped from her. People still waved and bowed, cheering and laughing, throwing flowers and other nonsense before their horses. She had difficulty breathing. Sooner than she would have liked, the iron and glass gate of the castle appeared, latticework doors opened, and a dozen guards flanked the cobblestone path that led through the archway. Spears erect, they held rectangular shields, and their eyes were dark beneath bronze helmets. Each wore a red cape. Their armor, while tarnished, was well crafted from copper and leather. Beyond the archway sloped a road, lined with trees of gold and silver.", "entities": [{"start": 104, "end": 111, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 908, "end": 919, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Pirate Lord"}], "chapter_id": "C07.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Chapter 8 Celaena walked down a marble hall, her dress flowing behind in a purple and white wave. Chaol strode beside her, a hand on the eagle-shaped pommel of his sword. “Is there anything interesting down this hall?” “What else would you care to see? We've already seen all three gardens, the ballrooms, the historical rooms, and the nicest views offered from the stone castle. If you refuse to go into the glass castle, there's nothing else to see.” She crossed her arms. She'd managed to convince him to give her a tour under the pretense of extreme boredom—when, in fact, she'd used every moment to plot a dozen escape routes from her room. The castle was old, and most of its halls and stairwells went nowhere; escaping would require some thought. But with the competition beginning tomorrow, what else did she have to do? And what better way to prepare for a potential disaster? “Idon't understand why you refuse to enter the glass addition,” he went on. “There's no difference between the interiors—you wouldn't even know that you were inside it unless someone told you or you looked out the window.” “Only an idiot would walk in a house made of glass.” “It's as sturdy as steel and stone.” “Yes, until someone just a bit too heavy enters and it comes crashing down.” “That's impossible.” The thought of standing on floors of glass made her queasy. “Is there no menagerie or library that we could see?” They passed by a set of closed doors. The sounds of lilting speech reached them, along with the gentle strumming of a harp.", "entities": [{"start": 10, "end": 17, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 98, "end": 103, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}], "chapter_id": "C08.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“What's in there?” “The queen's court.” He grabbed her arm and pulled her down the hall. “Queen Georgina?” Didn't he have any idea what information he was giving away? Perhaps he honestly thought she wasn't a threat. She hid her scowl. “Yes, Queen Georgina Havilliard.” “Is the young prince at home?” “Hollin? He's at school.” “And is he as handsome as his older brother?” Celaena smirked as Chaol tensed. It was well known that the ten-year-old prince was rotten and spoiled, inside and out, and she remembered the scandal that had erupted a few months before her capture. Hollin Havilliard, upon finding his porridge burnt, had beaten one of his servants so badly that there was no possibility of it being concealed. The woman's family had been paid off, and the young prince shipped to school in the mountains. Of course everyone knew. Queen Georgina had refused to hold court for a month. “Hollin will grow into his lineage,” Chaol grumbled. There was a bounce to her step as Celaena walked on, the court fading away behind them. They were silent for a few minutes before an explosion sounded nearby, then another. “What is that awful noise?” Celaena said. The captain led her through a set of glass doors, and he pointed up as they entered into a garden. “The clock tower,” he said, his bronze eyes shining with amusement, as the clock finished its war cry. She'd never heard bells like that. From the garden sprouted a tower made of inky black stone. Two gargoyles, wings spread for flight, perched on each of the four clock faces, soundlessly roaring at those beneath.", "entities": [{"start": 90, "end": 104, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Queen Georgina"}, {"start": 242, "end": 256, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Queen Georgina"}, {"start": 242, "end": 267, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Queen Georgina Havilliard"}, {"start": 302, "end": 308, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Hollin"}, {"start": 373, "end": 380, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 392, "end": 397, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 574, "end": 591, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Hollin Havilliard"}, {"start": 574, "end": 580, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Hollin"}, {"start": 839, "end": 853, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Queen Georgina"}, {"start": 894, "end": 900, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Hollin"}, {"start": 930, "end": 935, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 980, "end": 987, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1147, "end": 1154, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C08.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“What a horrible thing,” she whispered. The numbers were like war paint on the white face of the clock, the hands like swords as they slashed across the pearly surface. “As a child, Iwouldn't go near it,” Chaol admitted. “You'd see something like this before the Gates of Wyrd —not in a garden. How old is it?” “The king had it built around Dorian's birth.” “This king?” Chaol nodded. “Why would he build such a wretched thing?” “Come on,” he said, turning as he ignored her question. “Let's go.” Celaena examined the clock for a second more. The thick, clawed finger of a gargoyle pointed at her. She could have sworn that its jaws had widened. As she made to follow Chaol, she noticed a tile on the paved path-way. “What's this?” He stopped. “What's what?” She pointed at the mark engraved on the slate. It was a circle with a vertical line through the middle that extended beyond the circumference. Both ends of the line were hooked, one directing downward, the other up. “What is this mark on the path here?” He walked around until he stood beside her. “Ihave no idea.” Celaena examined the gargoyle again. “He's pointing at it. What does the symbol mean?” “It means you're wasting my time,” he said. “It's probably some sort of decorative sundial.” “Are there other marks?” “If you looked, I'm sure you'd find them.” She allowed herself to be dragged from the garden, away from the shadow of the clock tower and into the marble halls of the castle. Try as she might, and walk as far as they did, she couldn't shake the feeling that those bulging eyes were still upon her.", "entities": [{"start": 205, "end": 210, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 272, "end": 276, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Wyrd"}, {"start": 341, "end": 347, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 371, "end": 376, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 497, "end": 504, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 668, "end": 673, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 1074, "end": 1081, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C08.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Chapter 9 Celaena stood before the rosewood mirror, smiling. She ran a hand down her gown. Sea-foam white lace bloomed from the sweeping neck-line, washing upon her breast from the powder-green ocean of silk that made up the dress. Ared sash covered the waist, forming an inverted peak that separated the bodice from the explosion of skirts beneath. Patterns of clear green beads were embroidered in whorls and vines across the whole of it, and bone-colored stitching stretched along the ribs. Tucked inside her bodice was the small makeshift hairpin dagger, though it poked mercilessly at her chest. She lifted her hands to touch her curled and pinned hair. She didn't know what she planned to do now that she was dressed, especially if she'd probably have to change before the competition started, but— Skirts rustled from the doorway, and Celaena raised her eyes in the reflection to see Philippa enter behind her. The assassin tried not to preen —and failed miserably. “It's such a pity you are who you are,” Philippa said, turning Celaena to face her. “Iwouldn't be surprised if you managed to ensnare some lord into marriage. Maybe even His Highness, if you were charming enough.” She adjusted the green folds of Celaena's dress before kneeling down to brush the assassin's ruby-colored slippers. “Well, it seems rumor has already suggested that. Ioverheard a girl saying that the Crown Prince brought me here to woo me. Ithought the entire court knew about this stupid competition.” Philippa rose. “Whatever the rumors are, it'll all be forgotten in a week—just you wait.", "entities": [{"start": 10, "end": 17, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 842, "end": 849, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 891, "end": 899, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Philippa"}, {"start": 1013, "end": 1021, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Philippa"}, {"start": 1036, "end": 1043, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1219, "end": 1226, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1490, "end": 1498, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Philippa"}], "chapter_id": "C09.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Let him find a new woman he likes and you'll vanish from the whisperings of the court.” Celaena straightened as Philippa fixed a stray curl. “Oh, it's not meant as an offense, poppet. Beautiful ladies are always associated with the Crown Prince—you should be flattered that you're attractive enough to be considered his lover.” “I'd rather not be seen that way at all.” “Better than as an assassin, I'd wager.” She looked at Philippa and then laughed. Philippa shook her head. “Your face is much more pretty when you smile. Girlish, even. Far better than that frown you always have.” “Yes,” Celaena admitted, “you might be right.” She made to sit down upon the mauve ottoman. “Ah!” Philippa said, and Celaena froze, standing upright. “You'll wrinkle the fabric.” “But my feet hurt in these shoes.” She frowned pitifully. “You can't intend for me to stand all day? Even through my meals?” “Only until someone tells me how lovely you look.” “No one knows you're my servant.” “Oh, they know I've been assigned to the lover the prince brought to Rifthold.” Celaena chewed on her lip. Was it a good thing that no one knew who she truly was? What would her competition think? Perhaps a tunic and pants would have been better. Celaena reached to move a curl that itched her cheek, and Philippa batted her hand away. “You'll ruin your hair.” The doors to her apartment slammed open, followed by an already familiar snarling and stomping about. She watched in the mirror as Chaol appeared in the doorway, panting. Philippa curtsied. “You,” he began, then stopped as Celaena faced him.", "entities": [{"start": 88, "end": 95, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 112, "end": 120, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Philippa"}, {"start": 425, "end": 433, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Philippa"}, {"start": 452, "end": 460, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Philippa"}, {"start": 591, "end": 598, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 682, "end": 690, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Philippa"}, {"start": 701, "end": 708, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1042, "end": 1050, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Rifthold"}, {"start": 1053, "end": 1060, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1220, "end": 1227, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1278, "end": 1286, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Philippa"}, {"start": 1465, "end": 1470, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 1505, "end": 1513, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Philippa"}, {"start": 1557, "end": 1564, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C09.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "His brows lowered as his eyes traveled along her body. His head cocked, and he opened his mouth as if to say something, but only shook his head and scowled. “Upstairs. Now.” She curtsied, looking up at him beneath lowered lashes. “Where, pray tell, are we going?” “Oh, don't simper at me.” He grabbed her by the arm, guiding her out of the room. “Captain Westfall!” Philippa scolded. “She'll trip on her dress. At least let her hold her skirts.” She actually did trip on her dress, and her shoes cut into her heels quite terribly, but he would hear none of her objections as he dragged her into the hall. She smiled at the guards outside her door, and her smile burst into a grin at their exchanged approving glances. The captain's grip tightened until it hurt. “Hurry,” he said. “We can't be late.” “Perhaps if you'd given me ample warning, I'd have dressed earlier and you wouldn't have to drag me!” It was hard to breathe with the corset crushing her ribs. As they hurried up a long staircase, she raised a hand to her hair to ensure that it hadn't fallen out. “My mind was elsewhere; you were fortunate to be dressed, though Iwish you'd worn something less… frilly to see the king.” “The king?” She was thankful that she hadn't yet eaten. “Yes, the king. Did you think you wouldn't see him? The Crown Prince told you the competition was to start today —this meeting will mark the official beginning. The real work begins tomorrow.” Her arms became heavy and she forgot all about her aching feet and crushed ribs. In the garden, the queer, off-kilter clock tower began chiming the hour.", "entities": [{"start": 347, "end": 363, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Captain Westfall"}, {"start": 366, "end": 374, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Philippa"}], "chapter_id": "C09.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Chapter 10 She saw the floor first. Red marble, its white veins illuminated in the light of the sun, which slowly vanished as the opaque glass doors groaned shut. Chandeliers and torches hung all around. Her eyes darted from one side of the large, crowded chamber to the next. There were no windows, just a wall of glass looking out into nothing but sky. No escape, save for the door behind her. To her left, a fireplace occupied most of the wall, and as Chaol led her farther into the room, Celaena tried not to stare at the thing. It was monstrous, shaped like a roaring, fanged mouth, a blazing fire burning within. There was something greenish about the flame, something that made her spine straighten. The captain stopped in the open space before the throne, and Celaena halted with him. He didn't seem to notice their ominous surroundings, or if he did, he hid it far better. She pulled her gaze forward, taking in the crowd that filled the room. Stiffly, knowing that many eyes were upon her, Celaena dropped into a low bow, her skirts whispering. She found her legs weak when Chaol put a hand on her back to motion her to rise. He led her from the center of the room, where they took up a spot beside Dorian Havilliard. The absence of dirt and three weeks' worth of hard travel had a noticeable effect on his smooth face. He wore a red-and-gold jacket, his black hair brushed and shining. An expression of surprise crossed his features when he beheld her in her finery, but it quickly melted into a wry grin as he looked toward his father.", "entities": [{"start": 455, "end": 460, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 492, "end": 499, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 768, "end": 775, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1000, "end": 1007, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 1084, "end": 1089, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 1209, "end": 1226, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian Havilliard"}, {"start": 1209, "end": 1215, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}], "chapter_id": "C10.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "She might have returned it, had she not been focusing so much on keeping her hands from shaking. The king spoke at last. “Now that you've all finally bothered to arrive, perhaps we can begin.” It was a voice she had heard before, deep and raspy. It made her bones crack and splinter, made her feel the astonishing cold of a winter long since past. Her eyes only dared to venture as far as his chest. It was broad, not entirely with muscle, and seemed tightly restrained within a crimson and black tunic. Acape of white fur hung from his shoulders, and a sword was sheathed at his side. Atop its hilt perched a wyvern, open-mouthed and screaming. None that came before that broad blade lived to see another day. She knew that sword. Nothung was its name. “You have all been retrieved from across Erilea for the purpose of serving your country.” It was easy enough to tell the nobility from her competitors. Old and wrinkled, each nobleman wore fine clothes and decorative swords. Beside each of them stood a man—some tall and slender, some burly, some average, all of them surrounded by at least three vigilant guards. Twenty-three men stood between her and freedom. Most of them had enough bulk to warrant a double take, but when she scanned their faces—often scarred, pockmarked, or just plain hideous—there was no spark behind their eyes, no shining kernel of cleverness. They'd been picked for muscles, not brains. Three of them were actually in chains. Were they that dangerous?", "entities": [{"start": 732, "end": 739, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nothung"}, {"start": 795, "end": 801, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Erilea"}], "chapter_id": "C10.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Afew of them met her gaze, and she stared right back, wondering if they thought she was a competitor or just a court lady. Most of the competitors' attention jumped right over her. She gritted her teeth. The dress had been a mistake. Why had Chaol not told her about the meeting yesterday ? Amoderately handsome black-haired young man stared at her, though, and she willed her face into neutrality while his gray eyes took her in. He was tall and lean, but not gangly, and he inclined his head to her. She studied him for a moment longer, from the way he balanced his weight to his left, to what feature he first noticed when his eyes moved on and he examined the other competitors. One was a gargantuan man standing beside Duke Perrington, who seemed crafted of muscle and steel—and took pains to display it with his sleeveless armor. The man's arms looked capable of crushing a horse's skull. It wasn't that he was ugly—in fact, his tanned face was rather pleasant, but there was something nasty about his demeanor, about his obsidian eyes as they shifted and met her own. His large, white teeth gleamed. The king spoke. “You are each competing for the title of my Champion—my right-hand sword in a world brimming with enemies.” Aflicker of shame sparked within her. What was “Champion” but a dressed-up name for murderer? Could she actually stomach working for him? She swallowed. She had to. She had no other choice. “Over the next thirteen weeks, you shall each dwell and compete in my home.", "entities": [{"start": 242, "end": 247, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 724, "end": 739, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Duke Perrington"}, {"start": 729, "end": 739, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Perrington"}], "chapter_id": "C10.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Celaena offered her a slight smile, and the princess stepped closer, her guards tensing slightly. She moved with an easy grace. Kaltain gestured to the girl, poorly hidden distaste written across her beautiful face. “This is Her Royal Highness the Princess Nehemia Ytger of Eyllwe.” Chaol bowed low. The princess nodded, barely a dip of her chin. Celaena knew the name—she had often heard the Eyllwe slaves in Endovier boast of Nehemia's beauty and bravery. Nehemia, the Light of Eyllwe, who would save them from their plight. Nehemia, who might someday pose a threat to the King of Adarlan's rule over her home country when she ascended to the throne. Nehemia, they whispered, who smuggled information and supplies to the rebel groups hiding in Eyllwe.", "entities": [{"start": 0, "end": 7, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 128, "end": 135, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 257, "end": 270, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia Ytger"}, {"start": 274, "end": 280, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 283, "end": 288, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 347, "end": 354, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 393, "end": 399, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 410, "end": 418, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 428, "end": 435, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 458, "end": 465, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 480, "end": 486, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 527, "end": 534, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 583, "end": 590, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 653, "end": 660, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 746, "end": 752, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}], "chapter_id": "C13.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Kaltain gestured to the girl, poorly hidden distaste written across her beautiful face. “This is Her Royal Highness the Princess Nehemia Ytger of Eyllwe.” Chaol bowed low. The princess nodded, barely a dip of her chin. Celaena knew the name—she had often heard the Eyllwe slaves in Endovier boast of Nehemia's beauty and bravery. Nehemia, the Light of Eyllwe, who would save them from their plight. Nehemia, who might someday pose a threat to the King of Adarlan's rule over her home country when she ascended to the throne. Nehemia, they whispered, who smuggled information and supplies to the rebel groups hiding in Eyllwe. But what was she doing here? “And the Lady Lillian,” Kaltain added briskly. Celaena dropped into the lowest curtsy she could give without falling and said in Eyllwe, “Welcome to Rifthold, Your Highness.” Princess Nehemia smiled slowly, and the others gaped.", "entities": [{"start": 0, "end": 7, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 129, "end": 142, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia Ytger"}, {"start": 146, "end": 152, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 155, "end": 160, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 219, "end": 226, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 265, "end": 271, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 282, "end": 290, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 300, "end": 307, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 330, "end": 337, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 352, "end": 358, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 399, "end": 406, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 455, "end": 462, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 525, "end": 532, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 618, "end": 624, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 679, "end": 686, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 702, "end": 709, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 784, "end": 790, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 804, "end": 812, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Rifthold"}, {"start": 839, "end": 846, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}], "chapter_id": "C13.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“This is Her Royal Highness the Princess Nehemia Ytger of Eyllwe.” Chaol bowed low. The princess nodded, barely a dip of her chin. Celaena knew the name—she had often heard the Eyllwe slaves in Endovier boast of Nehemia's beauty and bravery. Nehemia, the Light of Eyllwe, who would save them from their plight. Nehemia, who might someday pose a threat to the King of Adarlan's rule over her home country when she ascended to the throne. Nehemia, they whispered, who smuggled information and supplies to the rebel groups hiding in Eyllwe. But what was she doing here? “And the Lady Lillian,” Kaltain added briskly. Celaena dropped into the lowest curtsy she could give without falling and said in Eyllwe, “Welcome to Rifthold, Your Highness.” Princess Nehemia smiled slowly, and the others gaped.", "entities": [{"start": 41, "end": 54, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia Ytger"}, {"start": 58, "end": 64, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 67, "end": 72, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 131, "end": 138, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 177, "end": 183, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 194, "end": 202, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 212, "end": 219, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 242, "end": 249, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 264, "end": 270, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 311, "end": 318, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 367, "end": 374, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 437, "end": 444, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 530, "end": 536, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 591, "end": 598, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 614, "end": 621, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 696, "end": 702, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 716, "end": 724, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Rifthold"}, {"start": 751, "end": 758, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}], "chapter_id": "C13.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Celaena knew the name—she had often heard the Eyllwe slaves in Endovier boast of Nehemia's beauty and bravery. Nehemia, the Light of Eyllwe, who would save them from their plight. Nehemia, who might someday pose a threat to the King of Adarlan's rule over her home country when she ascended to the throne. Nehemia, they whispered, who smuggled information and supplies to the rebel groups hiding in Eyllwe. But what was she doing here? “And the Lady Lillian,” Kaltain added briskly. Celaena dropped into the lowest curtsy she could give without falling and said in Eyllwe, “Welcome to Rifthold, Your Highness.” Princess Nehemia smiled slowly, and the others gaped. The councilman beamed, wiping the sweat from his brow. Why hadn't they sent Nehemia with the Crown Prince, or even Perrington? Why was the princess herded around by Kaltain Rompier? “Thank you,” the princess replied, her voice low.", "entities": [{"start": 0, "end": 7, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 46, "end": 52, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 63, "end": 71, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 81, "end": 88, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 111, "end": 118, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 133, "end": 139, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 180, "end": 187, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 236, "end": 243, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 306, "end": 313, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 399, "end": 405, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 460, "end": 467, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 483, "end": 490, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 565, "end": 571, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 585, "end": 593, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Rifthold"}, {"start": 620, "end": 627, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 741, "end": 748, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 780, "end": 790, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Perrington"}, {"start": 830, "end": 845, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain Rompier"}], "chapter_id": "C13.xhtml", "chunk_index": 3, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Nehemia, they whispered, who smuggled information and supplies to the rebel groups hiding in Eyllwe. But what was she doing here? “And the Lady Lillian,” Kaltain added briskly. Celaena dropped into the lowest curtsy she could give without falling and said in Eyllwe, “Welcome to Rifthold, Your Highness.” Princess Nehemia smiled slowly, and the others gaped. The councilman beamed, wiping the sweat from his brow. Why hadn't they sent Nehemia with the Crown Prince, or even Perrington? Why was the princess herded around by Kaltain Rompier? “Thank you,” the princess replied, her voice low. “Iimagine you've had a long journey,” Celaena continued in Eyllwe. “Have you arrived today, Your Highness?” Nehemia's guards exchanged glances, and Nehemia's brows rose slightly.", "entities": [{"start": 0, "end": 7, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 93, "end": 99, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 154, "end": 161, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 177, "end": 184, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 259, "end": 265, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 279, "end": 287, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Rifthold"}, {"start": 314, "end": 321, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 435, "end": 442, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 474, "end": 484, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Perrington"}, {"start": 524, "end": 539, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain Rompier"}, {"start": 629, "end": 636, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 650, "end": 656, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 699, "end": 706, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 739, "end": 746, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}], "chapter_id": "C13.xhtml", "chunk_index": 4, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Celaena dropped into the lowest curtsy she could give without falling and said in Eyllwe, “Welcome to Rifthold, Your Highness.” Princess Nehemia smiled slowly, and the others gaped. The councilman beamed, wiping the sweat from his brow. Why hadn't they sent Nehemia with the Crown Prince, or even Perrington? Why was the princess herded around by Kaltain Rompier? “Thank you,” the princess replied, her voice low. “Iimagine you've had a long journey,” Celaena continued in Eyllwe. “Have you arrived today, Your Highness?” Nehemia's guards exchanged glances, and Nehemia's brows rose slightly. Not too many northerners spoke their language. “Yes, and the queen sent this one”—Nehemia jerked her head at Kaltain—“to bring me around with that sweating worm of a man as well.” The princess narrowed her eyes at the small councilman, who wrung his hands and dabbed his forehead with a handkerchief.", "entities": [{"start": 0, "end": 7, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 82, "end": 88, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 102, "end": 110, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Rifthold"}, {"start": 137, "end": 144, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 258, "end": 265, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 297, "end": 307, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Perrington"}, {"start": 347, "end": 362, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain Rompier"}, {"start": 452, "end": 459, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 473, "end": 479, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}, {"start": 522, "end": 529, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 562, "end": 569, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 675, "end": 682, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nehemia"}, {"start": 702, "end": 709, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}], "chapter_id": "C13.xhtml", "chunk_index": 5, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "I've told you already: it's foolish to have this competition at all.” “If you do not mind your tongue, I'll have her use you for practice.” “And then what? Have Hollin take the throne?” “Do not doubt me, Dorian,” his father challenged. “You might think this… girl can win, but you forget that Duke Perrington is sponsoring Cain. You would have been better off picking a Champion like him—forged in blood and iron on the battle-field. Atrue Champion.” Dorian stuffed his hands in his pockets. “Don't you find the title a little ridiculous, given that our 'Champions' are no more than criminals?” His father rose from his throne and pointed at the map painted on the far wall of his council chamber. “Iam the conqueror of this continent, and soon to be ruler of all Erilea. You will not question me.” Dorian, realizing how close he was to crossing a boundary between impertinence and rebellion—a boundary that he'd been very, very careful to maintain—mumbled his apologies.", "entities": [{"start": 161, "end": 167, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Hollin"}, {"start": 204, "end": 210, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 293, "end": 308, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Duke Perrington"}, {"start": 323, "end": 327, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 451, "end": 457, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 799, "end": 805, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}], "chapter_id": "C07.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“It's rather charming, don't you think?” When she didn't respond, the prince asked, “Do you find my home to your liking?” “It's very fine indeed,” she said dully. “ 'Very fine indeed'? Maybe Ishould move my Champion to even larger chambers.” “If it pleases you.” Dorian chuckled. “I'm glad to find that seeing your competition hasn't damaged that swagger of yours. What'd you make of Cain?” She knew whom he meant. “Perhaps you should start feeding me whatever Perrington is giving him.” When Dorian continued staring at her, she rolled her eyes. “Men of his size usually aren't very fast, or very nimble. He could knock me out in one punch, probably, but he'd have to be swift enough to catch me.” She gave Chaol a quick glance, daring him to challenge her claim, but Dorian answered. “Good. Ithought so. And what of the others? Any potential rivals? Some of the Champions have rather gruesome reputations.” “Everyone else looks pathetic,” she lied.", "entities": [{"start": 263, "end": 269, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 384, "end": 388, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 461, "end": 471, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Perrington"}, {"start": 493, "end": 499, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 708, "end": 713, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 769, "end": 775, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}], "chapter_id": "C10.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Swords, sword-breakers, axes, bows, pikes, hunting daggers, maces, spears, throwing knives, wooden staves… While she generally preferred the stealth of a dagger, she was familiar with every weapon here. She glanced around the sparring room and hid her grimace. So were most of the competitors, it seemed. As she inspected them, she caught a movement in the corner of her vision. Cain entered the hall, flanked by two guards and a scarred, burly man who must have been his trainer. She squared her shoulders as Cain strode straight toward her, his thick lips parting in a grin. “Good morning,” he said, his voice raspy and deep. His dark eyes snaked along her body, then found her face again. “I'd have thought you'd be running home by now.” She gave him a close-lipped smile. “The fun's just starting, isn't it?” Cain returned her smile and stalked off.", "entities": [{"start": 379, "end": 383, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 510, "end": 514, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 813, "end": 817, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}], "chapter_id": "C11.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "She glanced around the sparring room and hid her grimace. So were most of the competitors, it seemed. As she inspected them, she caught a movement in the corner of her vision. Cain entered the hall, flanked by two guards and a scarred, burly man who must have been his trainer. She squared her shoulders as Cain strode straight toward her, his thick lips parting in a grin. “Good morning,” he said, his voice raspy and deep. His dark eyes snaked along her body, then found her face again. “I'd have thought you'd be running home by now.” She gave him a close-lipped smile. “The fun's just starting, isn't it?” Cain returned her smile and stalked off. It would have been so, so easy. So easy to whirl and grab him by the neck and slam his face into the ground.", "entities": [{"start": 176, "end": 180, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 307, "end": 311, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 610, "end": 614, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}], "chapter_id": "C11.xhtml", "chunk_index": 3, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "She squared her shoulders as Cain strode straight toward her, his thick lips parting in a grin. “Good morning,” he said, his voice raspy and deep. His dark eyes snaked along her body, then found her face again. “I'd have thought you'd be running home by now.” She gave him a close-lipped smile. “The fun's just starting, isn't it?” Cain returned her smile and stalked off. It would have been so, so easy. So easy to whirl and grab him by the neck and slam his face into the ground. She didn't even realize she was trembling with rage until Chaol stepped into her line of vision. “Save it for the competition,” he said softly, but not weakly. “I'm going to kill him,” she breathed. “No, you're not. If you want to shut him up, then beat him. He's just a brute from the king's army—don't waste your strength on hating him.” She rolled her eyes.", "entities": [{"start": 29, "end": 33, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 332, "end": 336, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 540, "end": 545, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}], "chapter_id": "C11.xhtml", "chunk_index": 4, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“Thank you so much for interfering on my behalf.” “You don't need me to rescue you.” “It still would have been nice.” “You can fight your own battles.” He pointed with his sword to the weapons rack. “Pick one.” His eyes shone with the challenge as she untied her cloak and tossed it behind her. “Let's see if you can actually back up your swaggering.” She'd shut Cain up—in an unmarked grave for all eternity. But for now… Now, she'd make Chaol eat his words. All the weapons were finely made, and glistened in the sunlight. Celaena eliminated her options one by one, seeing each weapon for what sort of damage she might do to the captain's face. Her heart beat rapidly as she ran a finger across the blades and handles of each. She found herself torn between the hunting daggers and a lovely rapier with an ornate bell-guard.", "entities": [{"start": 363, "end": 367, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 439, "end": 444, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 525, "end": 532, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C11.xhtml", "chunk_index": 5, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "She'd changed—she now wore a gown of white and gold that, despite herself, Celaena greatly admired. She was unfairly stunning. And Celaena was willing to bet a fortune that this was anything but a surprise —the woman had probably been waiting here for a while. “Lady Kaltain,” Dorian said tersely, his body tensing. “I've just come from Her Majesty's side,” said Kaltain, putting her back to Celaena. The assassin might have bothered to care about the slight if she had any interest in courtiers. “Her Majesty wishes to see Your Highness. Of course, Iinformed Her Majesty that Your Highness was in a meeting and could not be—” “Lady Kaltain,” interrupted Dorian, “I'm afraid you haven't been introduced to my friend.” Celaena could have sworn the young woman bristled.", "entities": [{"start": 75, "end": 82, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 131, "end": 138, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 267, "end": 274, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 277, "end": 283, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 363, "end": 370, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 392, "end": 399, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 633, "end": 640, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 655, "end": 661, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 718, "end": 725, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C10.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "She was unfairly stunning. And Celaena was willing to bet a fortune that this was anything but a surprise —the woman had probably been waiting here for a while. “Lady Kaltain,” Dorian said tersely, his body tensing. “I've just come from Her Majesty's side,” said Kaltain, putting her back to Celaena. The assassin might have bothered to care about the slight if she had any interest in courtiers. “Her Majesty wishes to see Your Highness. Of course, Iinformed Her Majesty that Your Highness was in a meeting and could not be—” “Lady Kaltain,” interrupted Dorian, “I'm afraid you haven't been introduced to my friend.” Celaena could have sworn the young woman bristled. “Allow me to present the Lady Lillian Gordaina.", "entities": [{"start": 31, "end": 38, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 167, "end": 174, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 177, "end": 183, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 263, "end": 270, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 292, "end": 299, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 533, "end": 540, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 555, "end": 561, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 618, "end": 625, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C10.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“I've just come from Her Majesty's side,” said Kaltain, putting her back to Celaena. The assassin might have bothered to care about the slight if she had any interest in courtiers. “Her Majesty wishes to see Your Highness. Of course, Iinformed Her Majesty that Your Highness was in a meeting and could not be—” “Lady Kaltain,” interrupted Dorian, “I'm afraid you haven't been introduced to my friend.” Celaena could have sworn the young woman bristled. “Allow me to present the Lady Lillian Gordaina. Lady Lillian, meet Lady Kaltain Rompier.” Celaena curtsied, restraining the urge to keep walking; if she had to deal with too much courtly nonsense, she might be better off back in Endovier. Kaltain bowed, the gold streaks in her dress glistening in the sunlight. “Lady Lillian is from Bellhaven—she arrived just yesterday.” The woman studied Celaena from beneath dark, shaped eyebrows.", "entities": [{"start": 47, "end": 54, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 76, "end": 83, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 317, "end": 324, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 339, "end": 345, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 402, "end": 409, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 525, "end": 540, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain Rompier"}, {"start": 543, "end": 550, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 682, "end": 690, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 692, "end": 699, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 844, "end": 851, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C10.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Of course, Iinformed Her Majesty that Your Highness was in a meeting and could not be—” “Lady Kaltain,” interrupted Dorian, “I'm afraid you haven't been introduced to my friend.” Celaena could have sworn the young woman bristled. “Allow me to present the Lady Lillian Gordaina. Lady Lillian, meet Lady Kaltain Rompier.” Celaena curtsied, restraining the urge to keep walking; if she had to deal with too much courtly nonsense, she might be better off back in Endovier. Kaltain bowed, the gold streaks in her dress glistening in the sunlight. “Lady Lillian is from Bellhaven—she arrived just yesterday.” The woman studied Celaena from beneath dark, shaped eyebrows. “And how long will you be staying with us?” “Only a few years,” Dorian said with a sigh.", "entities": [{"start": 94, "end": 101, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 116, "end": 122, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 179, "end": 186, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 302, "end": 317, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain Rompier"}, {"start": 320, "end": 327, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 459, "end": 467, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Endovier"}, {"start": 469, "end": 476, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 621, "end": 628, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 729, "end": 735, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}], "chapter_id": "C10.xhtml", "chunk_index": 3, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“Lady Lillian is from Bellhaven—she arrived just yesterday.” The woman studied Celaena from beneath dark, shaped eyebrows. “And how long will you be staying with us?” “Only a few years,” Dorian said with a sigh. “ 'Only'! Why, Your Highness! How droll! That is a very long stretch of time!” Celaena studied Kaltain's narrow, narrow waist. Was it really that small? Or could she barely breathe in her corset? She caught a glance exchanged between the two men—exasperation, annoyance, condescension. “The Lady Lillian and Captain Westfall are very close companions,” Dorian said dramatically. To Celaena's delight, Chaol blushed. “It will feel short for them, Iassure you.” “And for you, Your Highness?” Kaltain said coyly. Aconcealed edge lingered beneath her voice.", "entities": [{"start": 79, "end": 86, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 187, "end": 193, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 291, "end": 298, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 307, "end": 314, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 565, "end": 571, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dorian"}, {"start": 594, "end": 601, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 613, "end": 618, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 702, "end": 709, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}], "chapter_id": "C10.xhtml", "chunk_index": 4, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "By that afternoon, a vicious rainstorm arrived, and Chaol permitted Celaena to walk around the castle with him after she'd finished training with the other Champions for the day. Though he spoke little, she was glad to be out of her rooms, and dressed in one of her new gowns—a lovely lilac silk dress with pale pink lace accents and pearl beading. But then they rounded a corner and nearly collided with Kaltain Rompier. The assassin would have grimaced, but she forgot all about Kaltain as her eyes fell upon her companion. It was an Eyllwe woman. She was stunning, long and lean, each of her features perfectly formed and smooth. Her loose white dress contrasted with her creamy brown skin, and a three-plated gold torque covered much of her chest and neck. Bracelets of ivory and gold glimmered around her wrists, and her feet were sandaled beneath matching anklets.", "entities": [{"start": 52, "end": 57, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 68, "end": 75, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 405, "end": 420, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain Rompier"}, {"start": 481, "end": 488, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaltain"}, {"start": 536, "end": 542, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Eyllwe"}], "chapter_id": "C13.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "There were six more seasoned soldiers—all of them thrown out of the army for questionable behavior, which must have been truly questionable, given that Adarlan's army was notorious for ruthlessness. Then there were the three other thieves—including the dark-haired, gray-eyed Nox Owen, whom she'd actually heard of in passing, and who'd been giving her such charming smiles all morning. The three mercenaries looked ready to boil someone alive, and then there were the two shackled murderers. As his name suggested, Bill Chastain, the Eye Eater, ate the eyes of his victims. He looked surprisingly plain, with mousy brown hair, tan skin, and average height, though Celaena had trouble not staring at his scar-flecked mouth. The other murderer was Ned Clement, who'd gone for three years under the name Scythe, for the weapon he'd used to torture and hack apart temple priestesses.", "entities": [{"start": 152, "end": 159, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 276, "end": 284, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nox Owen"}, {"start": 665, "end": 672, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C12.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Without Chaol to stand near, she lingered beside a pillar, watching the competitors file in, flanked by guards and their trainers. Brullo wasn't there yet—another oddity. And there were far too many guards in the training hall today. “What do you suppose this is about?” Nox Owen, the young thief from Perranth, asked from beside her. After proving himself somewhat skilled during practice, many of the other competitors had sought him out, but he still opted to keep to himself. “Captain Westfall didn't train me this morning,” she offered. What was the harm in admitting that? Nox held out his hand. “Nox Owen.” “Iknow who you are,” she said, but shook his hand anyway. His grip was solid, his hand calloused and scarred.", "entities": [{"start": 8, "end": 13, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Chaol"}, {"start": 131, "end": 137, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Brullo"}, {"start": 271, "end": 279, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nox Owen"}, {"start": 302, "end": 310, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Perranth"}, {"start": 579, "end": 582, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nox"}, {"start": 603, "end": 611, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nox Owen"}], "chapter_id": "C14.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "After proving himself somewhat skilled during practice, many of the other competitors had sought him out, but he still opted to keep to himself. “Captain Westfall didn't train me this morning,” she offered. What was the harm in admitting that? Nox held out his hand. “Nox Owen.” “Iknow who you are,” she said, but shook his hand anyway. His grip was solid, his hand calloused and scarred. He'd seen his fair share of action. “Good. I've felt a bit invisible with that hulking lout showing off these past few days.” He jerked his chin toward Cain, who was in the middle of examining his bulging biceps. Alarge ring of black, iridescent stone glimmered on Cain's finger—strange that >he'd wear it to practice. Nox went on.", "entities": [{"start": 244, "end": 247, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nox"}, {"start": 268, "end": 276, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nox Owen"}, {"start": 541, "end": 545, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 654, "end": 658, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 708, "end": 711, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nox"}], "chapter_id": "C14.xhtml", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“What do you suppose this is about?” Nox Owen, the young thief from Perranth, asked from beside her. After proving himself somewhat skilled during practice, many of the other competitors had sought him out, but he still opted to keep to himself. “Captain Westfall didn't train me this morning,” she offered. What was the harm in admitting that? Nox held out his hand. “Nox Owen.” “Iknow who you are,” she said, but shook his hand anyway. His grip was solid, his hand calloused and scarred. He'd seen his fair share of action. “Good. I've felt a bit invisible with that hulking lout showing off these past few days.” He jerked his chin toward Cain, who was in the middle of examining his bulging biceps. Alarge ring of black, iridescent stone glimmered on Cain's finger—strange that >he'd wear it to practice.", "entities": [{"start": 37, "end": 45, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nox Owen"}, {"start": 68, "end": 76, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Perranth"}, {"start": 345, "end": 348, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nox"}, {"start": 369, "end": 377, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nox Owen"}, {"start": 642, "end": 646, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 755, "end": 759, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}], "chapter_id": "C14.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "I've felt a bit invisible with that hulking lout showing off these past few days.” He jerked his chin toward Cain, who was in the middle of examining his bulging biceps. Alarge ring of black, iridescent stone glimmered on Cain's finger—strange that >he'd wear it to practice. Nox went on. “Did you see Verin? He looks like he's going to be sick.” He pointed to the loudmouthed thief that Celaena wanted to knock out cold. Normally, Verin could be found near Cain, taunting the other Champions. But today he stood alone by the window, face pale and eyes wide. “Iheard him talking to Cain,” said a timid voice behind them, and they found Pelor, the youngest assassin, standing nearby. She'd spent half a day watching Pelor—and while she only pretended to be mediocre, he truly could use the training.", "entities": [{"start": 109, "end": 113, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 222, "end": 226, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 276, "end": 279, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Nox"}, {"start": 302, "end": 307, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Verin"}, {"start": 388, "end": 395, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 432, "end": 437, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Verin"}, {"start": 458, "end": 462, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}, {"start": 582, "end": 586, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cain"}], "chapter_id": "C14.xhtml", "chunk_index": 3, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "But no Fae had married into the Havilliard line for a thousand years, and there had been only one, and she was a half-breed at that. If this were true, if she was Fae or half-Fae, then she was… she was… Celaena stumbled back from the woman and slammed into the wall. Acoating of dust flew into the air around her. Then this man was Gavin, the first King of Adarlan. And this was Elena, the first princess of Terrasen, Brannon's daughter, and Gavin's wife and queen. Celaena's heart pounded so violently that she felt sick. But she couldn't make her feet move. She shouldn't have entered the tomb, she shouldn't have strayed into the sacred places of the dead when she was so stained and tainted by her crimes. Something would come after her, and haunt and torture her for disturbing their peace. But why was their tomb so neglected? Why had no one been to honor the dead this day? Why were there not flowers at her head? Why was Elena Galathynius Havilliard forgotten? Against the far wall of the chamber sat piles of jewels and weapons.", "entities": [{"start": 203, "end": 210, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 332, "end": 337, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Gavin"}, {"start": 357, "end": 364, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Adarlan"}, {"start": 379, "end": 384, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Elena"}, {"start": 408, "end": 416, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Terrasen"}, {"start": 442, "end": 447, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Gavin"}, {"start": 466, "end": 473, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 929, "end": 946, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Elena Galathynius"}], "chapter_id": "C25.xhtml", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Her silver hair flowed around her youthful face like a river of moonlight. Her eyes were a crystal, sparkling blue, and her skin was white as alabaster. And her ears were ever so slightly pointed. “Who are you?” the assassin breathed, knowing the answer, but wanting to hear it. “You know who Iam,” Elena Havilliard said. Her likeness had been perfectly rendered on the sarcophagus. Celaena didn't move from where she had fallen into the chest, despite her throbbing spine and legs. “Are you a ghost?” “Not quite,” said Queen Elena, helping Celaena rise from the chest. Her hand was cold, but solid. “I'm not alive, but my spirit doesn't haunt this place.” She flicked her eyes toward the ceiling, and her face became grave. “I've risked much coming here tonight.” Celaena, despite herself, took a step away.", "entities": [{"start": 299, "end": 315, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Elena Havilliard"}, {"start": 383, "end": 390, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 526, "end": 531, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Elena"}, {"start": 541, "end": 548, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}, {"start": 765, "end": 772, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Celaena"}], "chapter_id": "C25.xhtml", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "throne_of_glass", "language": "en"}
