{"text": "“Victory! We stand atop the mount! We scatter them before us! Their homes become our dens, their lands are now our farms! And they shall burn, as we once did, in a place that is hollow and forlorn.” —Collected on Ishashan, 1172, 18 seconds pre-death. Subject was a lighteyed spinster of the eighth dahn. Shallan's fears were confirmed as Jasnah looked straight at her, then lowered her safehand to her side in a mark of frustration. “So you are here.” Shallan cringed. “The servants told you, then?” “You didn't think that they would leave someone in my alcove and not warn me?” Behind Jasnah, a small group of parshmen hesitated in the hallway, each carrying an armload of books. “Brightness Kholin,” Shallan said. “Ijust—” “Ihave wasted enough time on you already,” Jasnah said, eyes furious. “You will withdraw, Miss Davar. And Iwill not see you again during my time here. Am Iunderstood ?” Shallan's hopes crumbled. She shrank back. There was a gravity to Jasnah Kholin. One did not disobey her. One need only look into those eyes to understand. “I'm sorry to have bothered you,” Shallan whispered, clutching her satchel and leaving with as much dignity as she could manage. She barely kept the tears of embarrassment and disappointment from her eyes as she hastened down the hallway, feeling like a complete fool. She reached the porter's shaft, though they had already returned below after bringing up Jasnah. Shallan didn't pull the bell to summon them. Instead she placed her back to the wall and sank down to the floor, knees up against her chest, satchel in her lap.", "entities": [{"start": 304, "end": 311, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 338, "end": 344, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 452, "end": 459, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 586, "end": 592, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 702, "end": 709, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 768, "end": 774, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 894, "end": 901, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 960, "end": 966, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 960, "end": 973, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah Kholin"}, {"start": 1084, "end": 1091, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1408, "end": 1414, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1416, "end": 1423, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}], "chapter_id": "id1115", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "She wrapped her arms around her legs, freehand clasping her safehand through the fabric of her cuff, breathing quietly. Angry people unsettled her. She couldn't help but think of her father in one of his tirades, couldn't help but hear screams, bellows, and whimpers. Was she weak because confrontation unsettled her so? She felt that she was. Foolish, idiot girl, she thought, a few painspren crawling out of the wall near her head. What made you think you could do this? You've only set foot off your family grounds a half-dozen times during your life. Idiot, idiot, idiot! She had persuaded her brothers to trust her, to put hope in her ridiculous plan. And now what had she done? Wasted six months during which their enemies circled closer. “Brightness Davar?” asked a hesitant voice. Shallan looked up, realizing she'd been so wrapped in her misery that she hadn't seen the servant approach. He was a younger man, wearing an all black uniform, no emblem on the breast. Not a master-servant, but perhaps one in training. “Brightness Kholin would like to speak with you.” The young man gestured back down the hallway. To berate me further? Shallan thought with a grimace. But a highlady like Jasnah got what she wanted. Shallan forced herself to stop shaking, then stood. At least she'd been able to keep the tears away; she hadn't ruined her makeup. She followed the servant back to the lit alcove, satchel clutched before her like a shield on the battlefield. Jasnah Kholin sat in the chair Shallan had been using, stacks of books on the table. Jasnah was rubbing her forehead with her freehand.", "entities": [{"start": 789, "end": 796, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1143, "end": 1150, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1195, "end": 1201, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1223, "end": 1230, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1465, "end": 1471, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1465, "end": 1478, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah Kholin"}, {"start": 1496, "end": 1503, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1550, "end": 1556, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}], "chapter_id": "id1115", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "The Soulcaster rested against the back of her skin, the smokestone dark and cracked. Though Jasnah looked fatigued, she sat with perfect posture, her fine silk dress covering her feet, her safehand held across her lap. Jasnah focused on Shallan, lowering her freehand. “Ishould not have treated you with such anger, Miss Davar,” she said in a tired voice. “You were simply showing persistence, a trait Inormally encourage. Storms alight, I've oft been guilty of stubbornness myself. Sometimes we find it hardest to accept in others that which we cling to in ourselves. My only excuse can be that Ihave put myself under an unusual amount of strain lately.” Shallan nodded in gratitude, though she felt terribly awkward. Jasnah turned to look out of the balcony into the dark space of the Veil. “Iknow what people say of me. Ishould hope that Iam not as harsh as some say, though a woman could have far worse than a reputation for sternness. It can serve one well.” Shallan had to forcibly keep herself from fidgeting. Should she withdraw? Jasnah shook her head to herself, though Shallan could not guess what thoughts had caused the unconscious gesture. Finally, she turned back to Shallan and waved toward the large, gobletlike bowl on the desk. It held a dozen of Shallan's spheres. Shallan raised her freehand to her lips in shock. She'd completely forgotten the money. She bowed to Jasnah in thanks, then hurriedly collected the spheres. “Brightness, lest Iforget, Ishould mention that an ardent—Brother Kabsal—came to see you while Iwaited here.", "entities": [{"start": 4, "end": 14, "label": "ORG", "text": "Soulcaster"}, {"start": 92, "end": 98, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 219, "end": 225, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 237, "end": 244, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 656, "end": 663, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 719, "end": 725, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 964, "end": 971, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1038, "end": 1044, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1079, "end": 1086, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1181, "end": 1188, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1265, "end": 1272, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1284, "end": 1291, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1385, "end": 1391, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1499, "end": 1513, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Brother Kabsal"}], "chapter_id": "id1115", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“They are aflame. They burn. They bring the darkness when they come, and so all you can see is that their skin is aflame. Burn, burn, burn….” —Collected on Palahishev, 1172, 21 seconds pre-death. Subject was a baker's apprentice. Shallan hurried down the hallway with its burnt-orange colorings, the ceiling and upper walls now stained by the passing of black smoke from Jasnah's Soulcasting. Hopefully, the paintings on the walls hadn't been ruined. Ahead, a small group of parshmen arrived, bearing rags, buckets, and stepladders to use in wiping off the soot. They bowed to her as she passed, uttering no words. Parshmen could speak, but they rarely did so. Many seemed mute. As a child, she'd found the patterns of their marbled skin beautiful. That had been before her father forbade her to spend any time with the parshmen. She turned her mind to her task. How was she going to convince Jasnah Kholin, one of the most powerful women in the world, to change her mind about taking Shallan as a ward? The woman was obviously stubborn; she had spent years resisting the devotaries' attempts at reconciliation. She reentered the broad main cavern, with its lofty stone ceiling and bustling, well-dressed occupants. She felt daunted, but that brief glimpse of the Soulcaster seduced her. Her family, House Davar, had prospered in recent years, coming out of obscurity. This had primarily been because of her father's skill in politics—he had been hated by many, but his ruthlessness had carried him far. So had the wealth lent by the discovery of several important new marble deposits on Davar lands.", "entities": [{"start": 230, "end": 237, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 371, "end": 377, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 615, "end": 623, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Parshmen"}, {"start": 893, "end": 899, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 893, "end": 906, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah Kholin"}, {"start": 985, "end": 992, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1264, "end": 1274, "label": "ORG", "text": "Soulcaster"}, {"start": 1300, "end": 1311, "label": "ORG", "text": "House Davar"}], "chapter_id": "id1116", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Shallan had never known enough to be suspicious of that wealth's origins. Every time the family had exhausted one of its quarries, her father had gone out with his surveyor and discovered a new one. Only after interrogating the surveyor had Shallan and her brothers discovered the truth: Her father, using his forbidden Soulcaster, had been creating new deposits at a careful rate. Not enough to be suspicious. Just enough to give him the money he needed to further his political goals. Nobody knew where he'd gotten the fabrial, which she now carried in her safepouch. It was unusable, damaged on the same disastrous evening that her father had died. Don't think about that, she told herself forcefully. They'd had a jeweler repair the broken Soulcaster, but it no longer worked. Their house steward—one of her father's close confidants, an advisor named Luesh—had been trained to use the device, and he could no longer make it function. Her father's debts and promises were outrageous. Their choices were limited. Her family had some time—perhaps as long as a year—before the missed payments became egregious, and before her father's absence became obvious. For once, her family's isolated, backcountry estates were an advantage, providing a reason that communications were being delayed. Her brothers were scrambling, writing letters in her father's name, making a few appearances and spreading rumors that Brightlord Davar was planning something big. All to give her time to make good on her bold plan. Find Jasnah Kholin. Become her ward. Learn where she kept her Soulcaster.", "entities": [{"start": 0, "end": 7, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 241, "end": 248, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 320, "end": 330, "label": "ORG", "text": "Soulcaster"}, {"start": 744, "end": 754, "label": "ORG", "text": "Soulcaster"}, {"start": 856, "end": 861, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Luesh"}, {"start": 1512, "end": 1518, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1569, "end": 1579, "label": "ORG", "text": "Soulcaster"}], "chapter_id": "id1116", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Then replace it with the nonfunctional one. With the fabrial, they'd be able to make new quarries and restore their wealth. They'd be able to make food to feed their house soldiers. With enough wealth in hand to pay off debts and make bribes, they could announce their father's death and not suffer destruction. Shallan hesitated in the main hallway, considering her next move. What she planned to do was very risky. She'd have to escape without implicating herself in the theft. Though she'd devoted much thought to that, she still didn't know how she'd manage it. But Jasnah was known to have many enemies. There had to be a way to pin the fabrial's “breaking” on them instead. That step would come later. For now, Shallan had to convince Jasnah to accept her as a ward. All other results were unacceptable. Nervously, Shallan held her arms in the sign of need, covered safehand bent across her chest and touching the elbow of her freehand, which was raised with fingers outspread. Awoman approached, wearing the well-starched white laced shirt and black skirt that were the universal sign of a master-servant. The stout woman curtsied. “Brightness?” “The Palanaeum,” Shallan said. The woman bowed and led Shallan farther into the depths of the long hallway. Most of the women here—servants included—wore their hair bound, and Shallan felt conspicuous with hers loose. The deep red color made her stand out even more. Soon, the grand hallway began to slope down steeply. But when the half-hour arrived, she could still hear distant bells ring behind her.", "entities": [{"start": 312, "end": 319, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 570, "end": 576, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 717, "end": 724, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 741, "end": 747, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 821, "end": 828, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1170, "end": 1177, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1208, "end": 1215, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1329, "end": 1336, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}], "chapter_id": "id1116", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“I'm cold. Mother, I'm cold. Mother? Why can Istill hear the rain? Will it stop?” —Collected on Vevishes, 1172, 32 seconds pre-death. Subject was a lighteyed female child, approximately six years old. Tvlakv released all of the slaves from their cages at once. This time, he didn't fear runaways or a slave rebellion—not with nothing but wilderness behind them and over a hundred thousand armed soldiers just ahead. Kaladin stepped down from the wagon. They were inside one of the craterlike formations, its jagged stone wall rising just to the east. The ground had been cleared of plant life, and the rock was slick beneath his unshod feet. Pools of rainwater had gathered in depressions. The air was crisp and clean, and the sun strong overhead, though with this Eastern humidity, he always felt damp. Around them spread the signs of an army long settled; this war had been going on since the old king's death, nearly six years ago. Everyone told stories of that night, the night when Parshendi tribesmen had murdered King Gavilar. Squads of soldiers marched by, following directions indicated by painted circles at each intersection. The camp was packed with long stone bunkers, and there were more tents than Kaladin had discerned from above. Soulcasters couldn't be used to create every shelter. After the stink of the slave caravan, the place smelled good, brimming with familiar scents like treated leather and oiled weapons. However, many of the soldiers had a disorderly look. They weren't dirty, but they didn't seem particularly disciplined either.", "entities": [{"start": 201, "end": 207, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}, {"start": 416, "end": 423, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 987, "end": 996, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Parshendi"}, {"start": 1020, "end": 1032, "label": "PERSON", "text": "King Gavilar"}, {"start": 1213, "end": 1220, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1247, "end": 1258, "label": "ORG", "text": "Soulcasters"}], "chapter_id": "id1117", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "They roamed the camp in packs with coats undone. Some pointed and jeered at the slaves. This was the army of a highprince? The elite force that fought for Alethkar's honor? This was what Kaladin had aspired to join? Bluth and Tag watched carefully as Kaladin lined up with the other slaves, but he didn't try anything. Now was not the time to provoke them—Kaladin had seen how mercenaries acted when around commissioned troops. Bluth and Tag played their part, walking with their chests out and hands on their weapons. They shoved a few of the slaves into place, ramming a cudgel into one man's belly and cursing him gruffly. They stayed clear of Kaladin. “The king's army,” said the slave next to him. It was the dark-skinned man who had talked to Kaladin about escaping. “Ithought we were meant for mine work. Why, this won't be so bad at all. We'll be cleaning latrines or maintaining roads.” Odd, to look forward to latrine work or labor in the hot sun. Kaladin hoped for something else. Hoped. Yes, he'd discovered that he could still hope. Aspear in his hands. An enemy to face. He could live like that. Tvlakv spoke with an important-looking lighteyed woman. She wore her dark hair up in a complex weave, sparkling with infused amethysts, and her dress was a deep crimson. She looked much as Laral had, at the end. She was probably of the fourth or fifth dahn, wife and scribe to one of the camp's officers. Tvlakv began to brag about his wares, but the woman raised a delicate hand. “Ican see what Iam purchasing, slaver,” she said in a smooth, aristocratic accent.", "entities": [{"start": 155, "end": 163, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Alethkar"}, {"start": 187, "end": 194, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 216, "end": 221, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Bluth"}, {"start": 226, "end": 229, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tag"}, {"start": 251, "end": 258, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 356, "end": 363, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 428, "end": 433, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Bluth"}, {"start": 438, "end": 441, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tag"}, {"start": 647, "end": 654, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 749, "end": 756, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 958, "end": 965, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1110, "end": 1116, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}, {"start": 1415, "end": 1421, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}], "chapter_id": "id1117", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“Iwill inspect them myself.” She began to walk down the line, accompanied by several soldiers. Her dress was cut in the Alethi noble fashion—a solid swath of silk, tight and formfitting through the top with sleek skirts below. It buttoned up the sides of the torso from waist to neck, where it was topped by a small, gold-embroidered collar. The longer left cuff hid her safehand. Kaladin's mother had always just worn a glove, which seemed far more practical to him. Judging by her face, she was not particularly impressed with what she saw. “These men are half-starved and sickly,” she said, taking a thin rod from a young female attendant. She used it to lift the hair from one man's forehead, inspecting his brand. “You are asking two emerald broams a head?” Tvlakv began to sweat. “Perhaps one and a half?” “And what would Iuse them for? Iwouldn't trust men this filthy near food, and we have parshmen to do most other work.” “If Your Ladyship is not pleased, Icould approach other highprinces….” “No,” she said, smacking the slave she'd been regarding as he shied away from her. “One and a quarter. They can help cut timber for us in the northern forests….” She trailed off as she noticed Kaladin. “Here now. This is far better stock than the others.” “Ithought that you might like this one,” Tvlakv said, stepping up to her. “He is quite—” She raised the rod and silenced Tvlakv. She had a small sore on one lip. Some ground cussweed root could help with that. “Remove your top, slave,” she commanded.", "entities": [{"start": 120, "end": 126, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}, {"start": 381, "end": 388, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 763, "end": 769, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}, {"start": 1195, "end": 1202, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1299, "end": 1305, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}, {"start": 1379, "end": 1385, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}], "chapter_id": "id1117", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“Ihave seen the end, and have heard it named. The Night of Sorrows, the True Desolation. The Everstorm.” —Collected on the 1st of Nanes, 1172, 15 seconds pre-death. Subject was a darkeyed youth of unknown origin. Shallan had not expected Jasnah Kholin to be so beautiful. It was a stately, mature beauty—as one might find in the portrait of some historical scholar. Shallan realized that she'd naively been expecting Jasnah to be an ugly spinster, like the stern matrons who had tutored her years ago. How else could one picture a heretic well into her mid-thirties and still unmarried? Jasnah was nothing like that. She was tall and slender, with clear skin, narrow black eyebrows, and thick, deep onyx hair. She wore part of it up, wrapped around a small, scroll-shaped golden ornament with two long hairpins holding it in place. The rest tumbled down behind her neck in small, tight curls. Even twisted and curled as it was, it came down to Jasnah's shoulders—if left unbound, it would be as long as Shallan's hair, reaching past the middle of her back. She had a squarish face and discriminating pale violet eyes. She was listening to a man dressed in robes of burnt orange and white, the Kharbranthian royal colors. Brightness Kholin was several fingers taller than the man—apparently, the Alethi reputation for height was no exaggeration. Jasnah glanced at Shallan, noting her, then returned to her conversation. Stormfather! This woman was the sister of a king. Reserved, statuesque, dressed immaculately in blue and silver.", "entities": [{"start": 213, "end": 220, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 238, "end": 251, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah Kholin"}, {"start": 238, "end": 244, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 366, "end": 373, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 417, "end": 423, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 587, "end": 593, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 944, "end": 950, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1003, "end": 1010, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1193, "end": 1203, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Kharbranth"}, {"start": 1295, "end": 1301, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}, {"start": 1345, "end": 1351, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1363, "end": 1370, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}], "chapter_id": "id1119", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Like Shallan's dress, Jasnah's buttoned up the sides and had a high collar, though Jasnah had a much fuller chest than Shallan. The skirts were loose below the waist, falling generously to the floor. Her sleeves were long and stately, and the left one was buttoned up to hide her safehand. On her freehand was a distinctive piece of jewelry: two rings and a bracelet connected by several chains, holding a triangular group of gemstones across the back of the hand. A Soulcaster—the word was used for both the people who performed the process and the fabrial that made it possible. Shallan edged into the room, trying to get a better look at the large, glowing gemstones. Her heart began to beat a little faster. The Soulcaster looked identical to the one she and her brothers had found in the inside pocket of her father's coat. Jasnah and the man in robes began walking in Shallan's direction, still talking. How would Jasnah react, now that her ward had finally caught up to her? Would she be angry because of Shallan's tardiness? Shallan couldn't be blamed for that, but people often expect irrational things from their inferiors. Like the grand cavern outside, this hallway was cut from the rock, but it was more richly furbished, with ornate hanging chandeliers made with Stormlit gemstones. Most were deep violet garnets, which were among the less valuable stones. Even so, the sheer number hanging there glistening with violet light would make the chandelier worth a small fortune.", "entities": [{"start": 5, "end": 12, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 22, "end": 28, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 83, "end": 89, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 119, "end": 126, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 467, "end": 477, "label": "ORG", "text": "Soulcaster"}, {"start": 581, "end": 588, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 716, "end": 726, "label": "ORG", "text": "Soulcaster"}, {"start": 829, "end": 835, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 874, "end": 881, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 920, "end": 926, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1012, "end": 1019, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1033, "end": 1040, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}], "chapter_id": "id1119", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "More than that, however, Shallan was impressed with the symmetry of the design and the beauty of the pattern of crystals hanging at the sides of the chandelier. As Jasnah grew near, Shallan could hear some of what she was saying. “…realize that this action might prompt an unfavorable reaction from the devotaries?” the woman said, speaking in Alethi. It was very near to Shallan's native Veden, and she'd been taught to speak it well during her childhood. “Yes, Brightness,” said the robed man. He was elderly, with a wispy white beard, and had pale grey eyes. His open, kindly face seemed very concerned, and he wore a squat, cylindrical hat that matched the orange and white of his robes. Rich robes. Was this some kind of royal steward, perhaps? No. Those gemstones on his fingers, the way he carried himself, the way other lighteyed attendants deferred to him… Stormfather! Shallan thought. This has to be the king himself! Not Jasnah's brother, Elhokar, but the king of Kharbranth. Taravangian. Shallan hastily performed an appropriate curtsy, which Jasnah noted. “The ardents have much sway here, Your Majesty,” Jasnah said with a smooth voice. “As do I,” the king said. “You needn't worry about me.” “Very well,” Jasnah said. “Your terms are agreeable. Lead me to the location, and Ishall see what can be done. If you will excuse me as we walk, however, Ihave someone to attend to.” Jasnah made a curt motion toward Shallan, waving her to join them. “Of course, Brightness,” the king said. He seemed to defer to Jasnah.", "entities": [{"start": 25, "end": 32, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 164, "end": 170, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 182, "end": 189, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 344, "end": 350, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}, {"start": 372, "end": 379, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 879, "end": 886, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 933, "end": 939, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 951, "end": 958, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Elhokar"}, {"start": 976, "end": 986, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Kharbranth"}, {"start": 988, "end": 999, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Taravangian"}, {"start": 1001, "end": 1008, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1056, "end": 1062, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1119, "end": 1125, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1221, "end": 1227, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1391, "end": 1397, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1424, "end": 1431, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1520, "end": 1526, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}], "chapter_id": "id1119", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“I'm dying, aren't I? Healer, why do you take my blood? Who is that beside you, with his head of lines? Ican see a distant sun, dark and cold, shining in a black sky.” —Collected on the 3rd of Jesnan, 1172, 11 seconds pre-death. Subject was a Reshi chull trainer. Sample is of particular note. “Why don't you cry?” the windspren asked. Kaladin sat with his back to the corner of the cage, looking down. The floor planks in front of him were splintered, as if someone had dug at them with nothing but his fingernails. The splintered section was stained dark where the dry grey wood had soaked up blood. Afutile, delusional attempt at escape. The wagon continued to roll. The same routine each day. Wake up sore and aching from a fitful night spent without mattress or blanket. One wagon at a time, the slaves were let out and hobbled with leg irons and given time to shuffle around and relieve themselves. Then they were packed away and given morning slop, and the wagons rolled until afternoon slop. More rolling. Evening slop, then a ladle of water before sleep. Kaladin's shash brand was still cracked and bleeding. At least the cage's top gave shade from the sun. The windspren shifted to mist, floating like a tiny cloud. She moved in close to Kaladin, the motion outlining her face at the front of the cloud, as if blowing back the fog and revealing something more substantial underneath. Vaporous, feminine, and angular. With such curious eyes. Like no other spren he'd seen. “The others cry at night,” she said. “But you don't.” “Why cry?” he said, leaning his head back against the bars.", "entities": [{"start": 336, "end": 343, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1064, "end": 1071, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1248, "end": 1255, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}], "chapter_id": "id1120", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“What would it change?” “Idon't know. Why do men cry?” He smiled, closing his eyes. “Ask the Almighty why men cry, little spren. Not me.” His forehead dripped with sweat from the Eastern summer humidity, and it stung as it seeped into his wound. Hopefully, they'd have some weeks of spring again soon. Weather and seasons were unpredictable. You never knew how long they would go on, though typically each would last a few weeks. The wagon rolled on. After a time, he felt sunlight on his face. He opened his eyes. The sun shone in through the upper side of the cage. Two or three hours past noon, then. What of afternoon slop? Kaladin stood, pulling himself up with one hand on the steel bars. He couldn't make out Tvlakv driving the wagon up ahead, only flat-faced Bluth behind. The mercenary had on a dirty shirt that laced up the front and wore a wide-brimmed hat against the sun, his spear and cudgel riding on the wagon bench beside him. He didn't carry a sword—not even Tvlakv did that, not near Alethi land. The grass continued to part for the wagons, vanishing just in front, then creeping out after the wagons passed. The landscape here was dotted with strange shrubs that Kaladin didn't recognize. They had thick stalks and stems and spiny green needles. Whenever the wagons grew too close, the needles pulled into the stalks, leaving behind twisted, wormlike trunks with knotted branches. They dotted the hilly landscape, rising from the grass-covered rocks like diminutive sentries. The wagons just kept on going, well past noon. Why aren't we stopping for slop?", "entities": [{"start": 628, "end": 635, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 716, "end": 722, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}, {"start": 767, "end": 772, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Bluth"}, {"start": 977, "end": 983, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}, {"start": 1003, "end": 1009, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}, {"start": 1183, "end": 1190, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}], "chapter_id": "id1120", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "The lead wagon finally pulled to a stop. The other two lurched to a halt behind it, the red-carapaced chulls fidgeted, their antennae waving back and forth. The box-shaped animals had bulging, stony shells and thick, trunklike red legs. From what Kaladin had heard, their claws could snap a man's arm. But chulls were docile, particularly domesticated ones, and he'd never known anyone in the army to get more than a halfhearted pinch from one. Bluth and Tag climbed down from their wagons and walked up to meet Tvlakv. The slavemaster stood on his wagon's seat, shading his eyes against the white sunlight and holding a sheet of paper in his hand. An argument ensued. Tvlakv kept waving in the direction they had been going, then pointing at his sheet of paper. “Lost, Tvlakv?” Kaladin called. “Perhaps you should pray to the Almighty for guidance. Ihear he has a fondness for slavers. Keeps a special room in Damnation just for you.” To Kaladin's left, one of the slaves—the long-bearded man who had talked to him a few days back—sidled away, not wanting to stand close to a person who was provoking the slaver. Tvlakv hesitated, then waved curtly to his mercenaries, silencing them. The portly man hopped down from his wagon and walked over to Kaladin. “You,” he said. “Deserter. Alethi armies travel these lands for their war. Do you know anything of the area?” “Let me see the map,” Kaladin said. Tvlakv hesitated, then held it up for Kaladin. Kaladin reached through the bars and snatched the paper. Then, without reading it, Kaladin ripped it in two.", "entities": [{"start": 247, "end": 254, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 445, "end": 450, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Bluth"}, {"start": 455, "end": 458, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tag"}, {"start": 512, "end": 518, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}, {"start": 669, "end": 675, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}, {"start": 770, "end": 776, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}, {"start": 779, "end": 786, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 939, "end": 946, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1114, "end": 1120, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}, {"start": 1247, "end": 1254, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1388, "end": 1395, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1402, "end": 1408, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tvlakv"}, {"start": 1440, "end": 1447, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1449, "end": 1456, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1532, "end": 1539, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}], "chapter_id": "id1120", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“Aman stood on a cliffside and watched his homeland fall into dust. The waters surged beneath, so far beneath. And he heard a child crying. They were his own tears.” —Collected on the 4th of Tanates, year 1171, thirty seconds before death. Subject was a cobbler of some renown. Kharbranth, City of Bells, was not a place that Shallan had ever imagined she would visit. Though she'd often dreamed of traveling, she'd expected to spend her early life sequestered in her family's manor, only escaping through the books of her father's library. She'd expected to marry one of her father's allies, then spend the rest of her life sequestered in his manor. But expectations were like fine pottery. The harder you held them, the more likely they were to crack. She found herself breathless, clutching her leather-bound drawing pad to her chest as longshoremen pulled the ship into the dock. Kharbranth was enormous. Built up the side of a steep incline, the city was wedge-shaped, as if it were built into a wide crack, with the open side toward the ocean. The buildings were blocky, with square windows, and appeared to have been constructed of some kind of mud or daub. Crem, perhaps? They were painted bright colors, reds and oranges most often, but occasional blues and yellows too. She could hear the bells already, tinkling in the wind, ringing with pure voices. She had to strain her neck to look up toward the city's loftiest rim; Kharbranth was like a mountain towering over her. How many people lived in a place like this? Thousands? Tens of thousands?", "entities": [{"start": 278, "end": 288, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Kharbranth"}, {"start": 326, "end": 333, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 884, "end": 894, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Kharbranth"}, {"start": 1432, "end": 1442, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Kharbranth"}], "chapter_id": "id1121", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "She shivered again—daunted yet excited—then blinked pointedly, fixing the image of the city in her memory. Sailors rushed about. The Wind's pleasure was a narrow, single-masted vessel, barely large enough for her, the captain, his wife, and the half-dozen crew. It had seemed so small at first, but Captain Tozbek was a calm and cautious man, an excellent sailor, even if he was a pagan. He'd guided the ship with care along the coast, always finding a sheltered cove to ride out highstorms. The captain oversaw the work as the men secured the mooring. Tozbek was a short man, even-shouldered with Shallan, and he wore his long white Thaylen eyebrows up in a curious spiked pattern. It was like he had two waving fans above his eyes, a foot long each. He wore a simple knit cap and a silver-buttoned black coat. She'd imagined him getting that scar on his jaw in a furious sea battle with pirates. The day before, she'd been disappointed to hear it had been caused by loose tackle during rough weather. His wife, Ashlv, was already walking down the gangplank to register their vessel. The captain saw Shallan inspecting him, and so walked over. He was a business connection of her family's, long trusted by her father. That was good, since the plan she and her brothers had concocted had contained no place for her bringing along a lady-in-waiting or nurse. That plan made Shallan nervous. Very, very nervous. She hated being duplicitous. But the financial state of her house…They either needed a spectacular infusion of wealth or some other edge in local Veden house politics.", "entities": [{"start": 307, "end": 313, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tozbek"}, {"start": 553, "end": 559, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tozbek"}, {"start": 598, "end": 605, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 634, "end": 641, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Thaylen"}, {"start": 1013, "end": 1018, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Ashlv"}, {"start": 1101, "end": 1108, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1373, "end": 1380, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1556, "end": 1561, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Veden"}], "chapter_id": "id1121", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Otherwise, they wouldn't last the year. First things first, Shallan thought, forcing herself to be calm. Find Jasnah Kholin. Assuming she hasn't moved off without you again. “I've sent a lad on your behalf, Brightness,” Tozbek said. “If the princess is still here, we shall soon know.” Shallan nodded gratefully, still clutching her drawing pad. Out in the city, there were people everywhere . Some wore familiar clothing—trousers and shirts that laced up the front for the men, skirts and colorful blouses for the women. Those could have been from her homeland, Jah Keved. But Kharbranth was a free city. Asmall, politically fragile city-state, it held little territory but had docks open to all ships that passed, and it asked no questions about nationality or status. People flowed to it. That meant many of the people she saw were exotic. Those single-sheet wraps would mark a man or woman from Tashikk, far to the west. The long coats, enveloping down to the ankles, but open in the front like cloaks…where were those from? She'd rarely seen so many parshmen as she noted working the docks, carrying cargo on their backs. Like the parshmen her father had owned, these were stout and thick of limb, with their odd marbled skin—some parts pale or black, others a deep crimson. The mottled pattern was unique to each individual. After chasing Jasnah Kholin from town to town for the better part of six months, Shallan was beginning to think she'd never catch the woman. Was the princess avoiding her? No, that didn't seem likely—Shallan just wasn't important enough to wait for.", "entities": [{"start": 60, "end": 67, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 110, "end": 123, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah Kholin"}, {"start": 220, "end": 226, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Tozbek"}, {"start": 286, "end": 293, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 563, "end": 572, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Jah Keved"}, {"start": 578, "end": 588, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Kharbranth"}, {"start": 899, "end": 906, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Tashikk"}, {"start": 1345, "end": 1358, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah Kholin"}, {"start": 1412, "end": 1419, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}, {"start": 1531, "end": 1538, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Shallan"}], "chapter_id": "id1121", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“Ten orders. We were loved, once. Why have you forsaken us, Almighty! Shard of my soul, where have you gone?” —Collected on the second day of Kakash, year 1171, five seconds before death. Subject was a lighteyed woman in her third decade. EIGHT MONTHS LATER Kaladin's stomach growled as he reached through the bars and accepted the bowl of slop. He pulled the small bowl—more a cup—between the bars, sniffed it, then grimaced as the caged wagon began to roll again. The sludgy grey slop was made from overcooked tallew grain, and this batch was flecked with crusted bits of yesterday's meal. Revolting though it was, it was all he would get. He began to eat, legs hanging out between the bars, watching the scenery pass. The other slaves in his cage clutched their bowls protectively, afraid that someone might steal from them. One of them tried to steal Kaladin's food on the first day. He'd nearly broken the man's arm. Now everyone left him alone. Suited him just fine. He ate with his fingers, careless of the dirt. He'd stopped noticing dirt months ago. He hated that he felt some of that same paranoia that the others showed. How could he not, after eight months of beatings, deprivation, and brutality? He fought down the paranoia. He wouldn't become like them. Even if he'd given up everything else—even if all had been taken from him, even if there was no longer hope of escape. This one thing he would retain. He was a slave. But he didn't need to think like one. He finished the slop quickly. Nearby, one of the other slaves began to cough weakly.", "entities": [{"start": 258, "end": 265, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 855, "end": 862, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}], "chapter_id": "id1122", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "There were ten slaves in the wagon, all men, scraggly-bearded and dirty. It was one of three wagons in their caravan through the Unclaimed Hills. The sun blazed reddish white on the horizon, like the hottest part of a smith's fire. It lit the framing clouds with a spray of color, paint thrown carelessly on a canvas. Covered in tall, monotonously green grass, the hills seemed endless. On a nearby mound, a small figure flitted around the plants, dancing like a fluttering insect. The figure was amorphous, vaguely translucent. Windspren were devious spirits who had a penchant for staying where they weren't wanted. He'd hoped that this one had gotten bored and left, but as Kaladin tried to toss his wooden bowl aside, he found that it stuck to his fingers. The windspren laughed, zipping by, nothing more than a ribbon of light without form. He cursed, tugging on the bowl. Windspren often played pranks like that. He pried at the bowl, and it eventually came free. Grumbling, he tossed it to one of the other slaves. The man quickly began to lick at the remnants of the slop. “Hey,” a voice whispered. Kaladin looked to the side. Aslave with dark skin and matted hair was crawling up to him, timid, as if expecting Kaladin to be angry. “You're not like the others.” The slave's black eyes glanced upward, toward Kaladin's forehead, which bore three brands. The first two made a glyphpair, given to him eight months ago, on his last day in Amaram's army. The third was fresh, given to him by his most recent master. Shash , the last glyph read. Dangerous.", "entities": [{"start": 529, "end": 538, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Windspren"}, {"start": 677, "end": 684, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 878, "end": 887, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Windspren"}, {"start": 1107, "end": 1114, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1220, "end": 1227, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1317, "end": 1324, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}], "chapter_id": "id1122", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "The slave had his hand hidden behind his rags. Aknife? No, that was ridiculous. None of these slaves could have hidden a weapon; the leaves hidden in Kaladin's belt were as close as one could get. But old instincts could not be banished easily, so Kaladin watched that hand. “Iheard the guards talking,” the slave continued, shuffling a little closer. He had a twitch that made him blink too frequently. “You've tried to escape before, they said. You have escaped before.” Kaladin made no reply. “Look,” the slave said, moving his hand out from behind his rags and revealing his bowl of slop. It was half full. “Take me with you next time,” he whispered. “I'll give you this. Half my food from now until we get away. Please.” As he spoke, he attracted a few hungerspren. They looked like brown flies that flitted around the man's head, almost too small to see. Kaladin turned away, looking out at the endless hills and their shifting, moving grasses. He rested one arm across the bars and placed his head against it, legs still hanging out. “Well?” the slave asked. “You're an idiot. If you gave me half your food, you'd be too weak to escape if Iwere to flee. Which Iwon't. It doesn't work.” “But—” “Ten times,” Kaladin whispered. “Ten escape attempts in eight months, fleeing from five different masters. And how many of them worked?” “Well…Imean…you're still here….” Eight months. Eight months as a slave, eight months of slop and beatings. It might as well have been an eternity. He barely remembered the army anymore. “You can't hide as a slave,” Kaladin said.", "entities": [{"start": 150, "end": 157, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 248, "end": 255, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 473, "end": 480, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 861, "end": 868, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1213, "end": 1220, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1552, "end": 1559, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}], "chapter_id": "id1122", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“You've killed me. Bastards, you've killed me! While the sun is still hot, Idie!” —Collected on the fifth day of the week Chach of the month Betab of the year 1171, ten seconds before death. Subject was a darkeyed soldier thirty-one years of age. Sample is considered questionable. FIVE YEARS LATER “I'm going to die, aren't I?” Cenn asked. The weathered veteran beside Cenn turned and inspected him. The veteran wore a full beard, cut short. At the sides, the black hairs were starting to give way to grey. I'm going to die, Cenn thought, clutching his spear—the shaft slick with sweat. I'm going to die. Oh, Stormfather. I'm going to die…. “How old are you, son?” the veteran asked. Cenn didn't remember the man's name. It was hard to recall anything while watching that other army form lines across the rocky battlefield. That lining up seemed so civil. Neat, organized. Shortspears in the front ranks, longspears and javelins next, archers at the sides. The darkeyed spearmen wore equipment like Cenn's: leather jerkin and knee-length skirt with a simple steel cap and a matching breastplate. Many of the lighteyes had full suits of armor. They sat astride horses, their honor guards clustering around them with breastplates that gleamed burgundy and deep forest green. Were there Shardbearers among them? Brightlord Amaram wasn't a Shardbearer. Were any of his men? What if Cenn had to fight one? Ordinary men didn't kill Shardbearers. It had happened so infrequently that each occurrence was now legendary. It's really happening, he thought with mounting terror. This wasn't a drill in the camp.", "entities": [{"start": 329, "end": 333, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 370, "end": 374, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 526, "end": 530, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 685, "end": 689, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 1000, "end": 1004, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 1285, "end": 1297, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Shardbearers"}, {"start": 1310, "end": 1327, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Brightlord Amaram"}, {"start": 1321, "end": 1327, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Amaram"}, {"start": 1379, "end": 1383, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 1427, "end": 1439, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Shardbearers"}], "chapter_id": "id1123", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "This wasn't training out in the fields, swinging sticks. This was real . Facing that fact—his heart pounding like a frightened animal in his chest, his legs unsteady—Cenn suddenly realized that he was a coward. He shouldn't have left the herds! He should never have— “Son?” the veteran said, voice firm. “How old are you?” “Fifteen, sir.” “And what's your name?” “Cenn, sir.” The mountainous, bearded man nodded. “I'm Dallet.” “Dallet,” Cenn repeated, still staring out at the other army. There were so many of them! Thousands. “I'm going to die, aren't I?” “ No .” Dallet had a gruff voice, but somehow that was comforting. “You're going to be just fine. Keep your head on straight. Stay with the squad.” “But I've barely had three months' training!” He swore he could hear faint clangs from the enemy's armor or shields. “Ican barely hold this spear! Stormfather, I'm dead . Ican't—” “Son,” Dallet interrupted, soft but firm. He raised a hand and placed it on Cenn's shoulder. The rim of Dallet's large round shield reflected the light from where it hung on his back. “You are going to be fine .” “How can you know?” It came out as a plea. “Because, lad. You're in Kaladin Stormblessed's squad.” The other soldiers nearby nodded in agreement. Behind them, waves and waves of soldiers were lining up—thousands of them. Cenn was right at the front, with Kaladin's squad of about thirty other men. Why had Cenn been moved to a new squad at the last moment? It had something to do with camp politics. Why was this squad at the very front, where casualties were bound to be the greatest?", "entities": [{"start": 166, "end": 170, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 364, "end": 368, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 418, "end": 424, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dallet"}, {"start": 428, "end": 434, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dallet"}, {"start": 437, "end": 441, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 566, "end": 572, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dallet"}, {"start": 893, "end": 899, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dallet"}, {"start": 962, "end": 966, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 990, "end": 996, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dallet"}, {"start": 1167, "end": 1174, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1167, "end": 1187, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin Stormblessed"}, {"start": 1320, "end": 1324, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 1354, "end": 1361, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 1405, "end": 1409, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}], "chapter_id": "id1123", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Small fearspren—like globs of purplish goo—began to climb up out of the ground and gather around his feet. In a moment of sheer panic, he nearly dropped his spear and scrambled away. Dallet's hand tightened on his shoulder. Looking up into Dallet's confident black eyes, Cenn hesitated. “Did you piss before we formed ranks?” Dallet asked. “Ididn't have time to—” “Go now.” “ Here? ” “If you don't, you'll end up with it running down your leg in battle, distracting you, maybe killing you. Do it.” Embarrassed, Cenn handed Dallet his spear and relieved himself onto the stones. When he finished, he shot glances at those next to him. None of Kaladin's soldiers smirked. They stood steady, spears to their sides, shields on their backs. The enemy army was almost finished. The field between the two forces was bare, flat slickrock, remarkably even and smooth, broken only by occasional rockbuds. It would have made a good pasture. The warm wind blew in Cenn's face, thick with the watery scents of last night's highstorm. “Dallet!” a voice said. Aman walked up through the ranks, carrying a shortspear that had two leather knife sheaths strapped to the haft. The newcomer was a young man—perhaps four years older than Cenn's fifteen—but he was taller by several fingers than even Dallet. He wore the common leathers of a spearman, but under them was a pair of dark trousers. That wasn't supposed to be allowed. His black Alethi hair was shoulder-length and wavy, his eyes a dark brown. He also had knots of white cord on the shoulders of his jerkin, marking him as a squadleader.", "entities": [{"start": 183, "end": 189, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dallet"}, {"start": 240, "end": 246, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dallet"}, {"start": 271, "end": 275, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 326, "end": 332, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dallet"}, {"start": 511, "end": 515, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 523, "end": 529, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dallet"}, {"start": 642, "end": 649, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kaladin"}, {"start": 952, "end": 956, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 1022, "end": 1028, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dallet"}, {"start": 1217, "end": 1221, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Cenn"}, {"start": 1279, "end": 1285, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dallet"}], "chapter_id": "id1123", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "“The love of men is a frigid thing, a mountain stream only three steps from the ice. We are his. Oh Stormfather…we are his. It is but a thousand days, and the Everstorm comes.” —Collected on the first day of the week Palah of the month Shash of the year 1171, thirty-one seconds before death. Subject was a darkeyed pregnant woman of middle years. The child did not survive. Szeth-son-son-Vallano, Truthless of Shinovar, wore white on the day he was to kill a king. The white clothing was a Parshendi tradition, foreign to him. But he did as his masters required and did not ask for an explanation. He sat in a large stone room, baked by enormous firepits that cast a garish light upon the revelers, causing beads of sweat to form on their skin as they danced, and drank, and yelled, and sang, and clapped. Some fell to the ground red-faced, the revelry too much for them, their stomachs proving to be inferior wineskins. They looked as if they were dead, at least until their friends carried them out of the feast hall to waiting beds. Szeth did not sway to the drums, drink the sapphire wine, or stand to dance. He sat on a bench at the back, a still servant in white robes. Few at the treaty-signing celebration noticed him. He was just a servant, and Shin were easy to ignore. Most out here in the East thought Szeth's kind were docile and harmless. They were generally right. The drummers began a new rhythm. The beats shook Szeth like a quartet of thumping hearts, pumping waves of invisible blood through the room.", "entities": [{"start": 375, "end": 380, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth"}, {"start": 375, "end": 396, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth-son-son-Vallano"}, {"start": 411, "end": 419, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Shinovar"}, {"start": 491, "end": 500, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Parshendi"}, {"start": 1037, "end": 1042, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth"}, {"start": 1315, "end": 1320, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth"}, {"start": 1430, "end": 1435, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth"}], "chapter_id": "id1125", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Szeth's masters—who were dismissed as savages by those in more civilized kingdoms—sat at their own tables. They were men with skin of black marbled with red. Parshendi, they were named—cousins to the more docile servant peoples known as parshmen in most of the world. An oddity. They did not call themselves Parshendi; this was the Alethi name for them. It meant, roughly, “parshmen who can think.” Neither side seemed to see that as an insult. The Parshendi had brought the musicians. At first, the Alethi lighteyes had been hesitant. To them, drums were base instruments of the common, darkeyed people. But wine was the great assassin of both tradition and propriety, and now the Alethi elite danced with abandon. Szeth stood and began to pick his way through the room. The revelry had lasted long; even the king had retired hours ago. But many still celebrated. As he walked, Szeth was forced to step around Dalinar Kholin—the king's own brother—who slumped drunken at a small table. The aging but powerfully built man kept waving away those who tried to encourage him to bed. Where was Jasnah, the king's daughter? Elhokar, the king's son and heir, sat at the high table, ruling the feast in his father's absence. He was in conversation with two men, a dark-skinned Azish man who had an odd patch of pale skin on his cheek and a thinner, Alethi-looking man who kept glancing over his shoulder. The heir's feasting companions were unimportant. Szeth stayed far from the heir, skirting the sides of the room, passing the drummers.", "entities": [{"start": 0, "end": 5, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth"}, {"start": 158, "end": 167, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Parshendi"}, {"start": 308, "end": 317, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Parshendi"}, {"start": 332, "end": 338, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}, {"start": 449, "end": 458, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Parshendi"}, {"start": 500, "end": 506, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}, {"start": 682, "end": 688, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}, {"start": 716, "end": 721, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth"}, {"start": 879, "end": 884, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth"}, {"start": 911, "end": 925, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Dalinar Kholin"}, {"start": 1090, "end": 1096, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jasnah"}, {"start": 1119, "end": 1126, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Elhokar"}, {"start": 1342, "end": 1348, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}, {"start": 1447, "end": 1452, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth"}], "chapter_id": "id1125", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "Musicspren zipped through the air around them, the tiny spirits taking the form of spinning translucent ribbons. As Szeth passed the drummers, they noted him. They would withdraw soon, along with all of the other Parshendi. They did not seem offended. They did not seem angry. And yet they were going to break their treaty of only a few hours. It made no sense. But Szeth did not ask questions. At the edge of the room, he passed rows of unwavering azure lights that bulged out where wall met floor. They held sapphires infused with Stormlight. Profane. How could the men of these lands use something so sacred for mere illumination? Worse, the Alethi scholars were said to be close to creating new Shardblades. Szeth hoped that was just wishful boasting. For if it did happen, the world would be changed. Likely in a way that ended with people in all countries—from distant Thaylenah to towering Jah Keved—speaking Alethi to their children. They were a grand people, these Alethi. Even drunk, there was a natural nobility to them. Tall and well made, the men dressed in dark silk coats that buttoned down the sides of the chest and were elaborately embroidered in silver or gold. Each one looked a general on the field. The women were even more splendid. They wore grand silk dresses, tightly fitted, the bright colors a contrast to the dark tones favored by the men. The left sleeve of each dress was longer than the right one, covering the hand. Alethi had an odd sense of propriety. Their pure black hair was pinned up atop their heads, either in intricate weavings of braids or in loose piles.", "entities": [{"start": 116, "end": 121, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth"}, {"start": 213, "end": 222, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Parshendi"}, {"start": 366, "end": 371, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth"}, {"start": 533, "end": 543, "label": "EVENT", "text": "Stormlight"}, {"start": 645, "end": 651, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}, {"start": 712, "end": 717, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Szeth"}, {"start": 875, "end": 884, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Thaylenah"}, {"start": 897, "end": 906, "label": "PLACE", "text": "Jah Keved"}, {"start": 916, "end": 922, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}, {"start": 974, "end": 980, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}, {"start": 1449, "end": 1455, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Alethi"}], "chapter_id": "id1125", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "PRELUDE TO THE STORMLIGHT ARCHIVE Kalak rounded a rocky stone ridge and stumbled to a stop before the body of a dying thunderclast. The enormous stone beast lay on its side, riblike protrusions from its chest broken and cracked. The monstrosity was vaguely skeletal in shape, with unnaturally long limbs that sprouted from granite shoulders. The eyes were deep red spots on the arrowhead face, as if created by a fire burning deep within the stone. They faded. Even after all these centuries, seeing a thunderclast up close made Kalak shiver. The beast's hand was as long as a man was tall. He'd been killed by hands like those before, and it hadn't been pleasant. Of course, dying rarely was. He rounded the creature, picking his way more carefully across the battlefield. The plain was a place of misshapen rock and stone, natural pillars rising around him, bodies littering the ground. Few plants lived here. The stone ridges and mounds bore numerous scars. Some were shattered, blasted-out sections where Surgebinders had fought. Less frequently, he passed cracked, oddly shaped hollows where thunderclasts had ripped themselves free of the stone to join the fray. Many of the bodies around him were human; many were not. Blood mixed. Red. Orange. Violet. Though none of the bodies around him stirred, an indistinct haze of sounds hung in the air. Moans of pain, cries of grief. They did not seem like the sounds of victory. Smoke curled from the occasional patches of growth or heaps of burning corpses. Even some sections of rock smoldered. The Dustbringers had done their work well.", "entities": [{"start": 34, "end": 39, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 529, "end": 534, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 1009, "end": 1021, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Surgebinders"}, {"start": 1551, "end": 1563, "label": "FACTION", "text": "Dustbringers"}], "chapter_id": "id1128", "chunk_index": 0, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "But Isurvived, Kalak thought, hand to breast as he hastened to the meeting place. Iactually survived this time. That was dangerous. When he died, he was sent back, no choice. When he survived the Desolation, he was supposed to go back as well. Back to that place that he dreaded. Back to that place of pain and fire. What if he just decided…not to go? Perilous thoughts, perhaps traitorous thoughts. He hastened on his way. The place of meeting was in the shadow of a large rock formation, a spire rising into the sky. As always, the ten of them had decided upon it before the battle. The survivors would make their way here. Oddly, only one of the others was waiting for him. Jezrien. Had the other eight all died? It was possible. The battle had been so furious this time, one of the worst. The enemy was growing increasingly tenacious. But no. Kalak frowned as he stepped up to the base of the spire. Seven magnificent swords stood proudly here, driven point-first into the stone ground. Each was a masterly work of art, flowing in design, inscribed with glyphs and patterns. He recognized each one. If their masters had died, the Blades would have vanished. These Blades were weapons of power beyond even Shardblades. These were unique. Precious. Jezrien stood outside the ring of swords, looking eastward. “Jezrien?” The figure in white and blue glanced toward him. Even after all these centuries, Jezrien looked young, like a man barely into his thirtieth year. His short black beard was neatly trimmed, though his once-fine clothing was scorched and stained with blood.", "entities": [{"start": 15, "end": 20, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 196, "end": 206, "label": "EVENT", "text": "Desolation"}, {"start": 677, "end": 684, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jezrien"}, {"start": 847, "end": 852, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 1251, "end": 1258, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jezrien"}, {"start": 1312, "end": 1319, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jezrien"}, {"start": 1403, "end": 1410, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jezrien"}], "chapter_id": "id1128", "chunk_index": 1, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}
{"text": "He folded his arms behind his back as he turned to Kalak. “What is this, Jezrien?” Kalak asked. “Where are the others?” “Departed.” Jezrien's voice was calm, deep, regal. Though he hadn't worn a crown in centuries, his royal manner lingered. He always seemed to know what to do. “You might call it a miracle. Only one of us died this time.” “Talenel,” Kalak said. His was the only Blade unaccounted for. “Yes. He died holding that passage by the northern waterway.” Kalak nodded. Taln had a tendency to choose seemingly hopeless fights and win them. He also had a tendency to die in the process. He would be back now, in the place where they went between Desolations. The place of nightmares. Kalak found himself shaking. When had he become so weak? “Jezrien, Ican't return this time.” Kalak whispered the words, stepping up and gripping the other man's arm. “Ican't .” Kalak felt something within him break at the admission. How long had it been? Centuries, perhaps millennia, of torture. It was so hard to keep track. Those fires, those hooks, digging into his flesh anew each day. Searing the skin off his arm, then burning the fat, then driving to the bone. He could smell it. Almighty, he could smell it! “Leave your sword,” Jezrien said. “What?” Jezrien nodded to the ring of weapons. “Iwas chosen to wait for you. We weren't certain if you had survived. A…a decision has been made. It is time for the Oathpact to end.” Kalak felt a sharp stab of horror. “What will that do?” “Ishar believes that so long as there is one of us still bound to the Oathpact, it may be enough.", "entities": [{"start": 51, "end": 56, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 73, "end": 80, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jezrien"}, {"start": 83, "end": 88, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 132, "end": 139, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jezrien"}, {"start": 342, "end": 349, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Talenel"}, {"start": 352, "end": 357, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 466, "end": 471, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 480, "end": 484, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Taln"}, {"start": 693, "end": 698, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 751, "end": 758, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jezrien"}, {"start": 786, "end": 791, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 870, "end": 875, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 1230, "end": 1237, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jezrien"}, {"start": 1252, "end": 1259, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Jezrien"}, {"start": 1408, "end": 1416, "label": "EVENT", "text": "Oathpact"}, {"start": 1426, "end": 1431, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Kalak"}, {"start": 1483, "end": 1488, "label": "PERSON", "text": "Ishar"}, {"start": 1552, "end": 1560, "label": "EVENT", "text": "Oathpact"}], "chapter_id": "id1128", "chunk_index": 2, "source": "the_way_of_kings", "language": "en"}